<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[History]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>History</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 09:50:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 09:50:04 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[III. Consequences of Agriculture]]></title><description><![CDATA[What might be consequences of people beginning to farm?Negative Feedback Loop
<img src="102-early-civilisations/resources/negative-feedback-loop.jpg" target="_self">
<br>Perennial Wheatgrass vs. Annual Wheat
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a7/4_Seasons_Roots.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Comparison of the root systems of Perennial Wheatgrass and Annual Wheat. This difference is important e.g. in the midwest of the USA, where the perennial wheatgrass was predominant and only replaced in the 19th and early 20th centuries. → what do you think consequences might be for soil and landscape after farmers started planting annual wheat instead of the perennial wheatgrass?
Explain the difference between the two sorts of wheat illustrated above and try to think about consequences
perennial wheatgrass: doesn’t die after the season; hibernates → massive roots
annual wheat: dies after season; seeds off
annual grasses: had bigger seeds → bigger yield
→ loss of root systems: more erosion, wind and water cary away most important top soil strati; flash floods, dust storms
]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/iii.-consequences-of-agriculture.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/III. Consequences of Agriculture.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 09:49:53 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IV. Cities and Civilisations]]></title><description><![CDATA[Task
Find out what the pictures below show
<img src="https://cdn.britannica.com/08/150008-050-D5A45539/Ziggurat-Ur.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved"><br>
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/b/bc/Luxor-Tempel_Pylon_08.jpg/1440px-Luxor-Tempel_Pylon_08.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved"><br>
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1f/Berl%C3%ADn%2C_Museo_de_P%C3%A9rgamo_05.jpg/1158px-Berl%C3%ADn%2C_Museo_de_P%C3%A9rgamo_05.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
First in the Tigris-Euphrates and Nile River valleys, then the Indus valley, and later in China’s Huang River (Huang He) valley and a few other regions, societies emerged that were far larger and denser than the farming communities of the Neolithic period. We refer to these big concentrations of people as complex societies, or, more traditionally, as civilisations.
Their most noticeable characteristic was cities. Early cities were centres of power, manufacturing, and creativity. Building and preserving them, however, required drastic alteration
s of the local environment to produce sufficient food, building materials, and sources of energy. The price of this intervention was high. Dense urban societies were extremely vulnerable to changes in weather, climate, disease conditions, wood supplies, and trade links to distant regions. After the appearance of complex societies, humans stepped up their efforts to manipulate and control their physical and natural environment. This had great benefits but also produced a negative feedback cycle.Dates
Among the oldest cities are
• Jericho (fortified ~8000)
• Çatal Hüyük (~7000)
•Ur (~5000)
• Byblos (5th millennium)
~5700
First proto-urban
architecture in Egypt
~5500
Neolithical settlements with long houses in Middle Europe
~4600
First city-like settlements in the Indus valley
~4300 to ~800 BC
Stilt house settlements in central Europe
~3800
Cultures in China
organized in cities
~3300
Glacier man “Ötzi”
~3100 to ~2600
Stonehenge
~3000
Sumerian city-states
~2600 – 1800
Mohenjo-Daro in the Indus valley, systematically planned city
The intensification of population and production obliged humans to experiment with new forms of social organization. The customs and rules that governed social relationships in a foraging band of twentyfive or thirty people were no longer adequate.After about 4000 BC, massive changes occur in social customs and institutions. The complex societies that arose in the Tigris-Euphrates, Nile, and Indus valleys, and somewhat later in other regions, were cauldrons of intensification. That is, people lived and worked together in much larger, denser communities than had ever existed. These societies shared a number of fundamental characteristics, which we generally associate with civilizations:
Cities arose, the early ones varying somewhat in their forms and functions. By 2250 BC, there were about eight cities in the world that had 30 000 or more inhabitants. By 1200 BC there were about sixteen cities that big.
Some people took up full-time specialized occupations and professions (artisans, merchants, soldiers, priests, and so on) rather than spending most of their time collecting, producing, or processing food.
A hierarchy of social classes (social stratification) appeared in which some men and women – the elite class – had more wealth, power, and privilege than did others. Also, men became dominant over women in political and social life, leading to patriarchy.
The state, that is, a centralized system of government and command, was invented. This meant that a minority group – kings, queens, high officials, priests, generals – exercised control over the labour and social behaviour of everyone else.
Complex exchanges of food and other products took place within the complex society, and lines of trade connected the society to neighbours near and far.
Technological innovations multiplied, and each new useful invention tended to suggest several others.
Monumental building took place – city walls, temples, palaces, public plazas, and tombs of rulers.
A system of writing, or at least a complex method of record-keeping, came into use.
Spiritual belief systems, public laws, and artistic expressions all became richer and more complex.
<br>Creative individuals collaborated with the ruling class to lay the foundations of astronomy, mathematics, and chemistry, as well as civil engineering and architecture.
Dates
(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="03 Antiquity Timelines > Ancient Civilizations" data-href="03 Antiquity Timelines#Ancient Civilizations" href="001-techniques/timelines/03-antiquity-timelines.html#Ancient Civilizations" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">see as timeline</a>)
~3000
Parallel development of cuneiform in Mesopotamia and hieroglyphs in Egypt
~2980
First unification of Upper and Lower Egypt (Old Kingdom)
~2650 – 2190
Time of the Pyramids
~2650 First step pyramid by Snofru
~2600 Cheops pyramid
2600 – ~1425
Minoan culture on Crete
~1900 – 1531
Babylonian Empire
~1700
Code of Hammurabi, earliest known law code
~1600
Mycenaean Culture,
earliest advanced civilization on mainland Europe
~1000 – 70 BC
Kingdom of Israel (with interruptions)
30 BC
Death of the last pharaoh, Cleopatra VII.
Egypt becomes a Roman province A society did not have to have every one of these characteristics to qualify as a civilization. The checklist is less important than the fact that all these social, cultural, economic, and political elements interacted dynamically with one another. The synergism among them made the society complex, that is, made it recognizable as a civilization.World population started growing at a faster rate than ever before. The size and density of communities expanded, and networks of communication by land and sea became more extensive and sophisticated. Along with these developments came, as we might well expect, an intensification in the flow of information and a general speed-up in the accumulation of knowledge of all kinds.
One example is religious knowledge. In the early millennia of this period certain ideas, practices, and artistic expressions centred on the worship of female deities spread widely along routes of trade and migration to embrace a large part of western Eurasia. Another example is the idea and technology of writing, which emerged first, as far as we know, in either Egypt or Mesopotamia and spread widely from there to the eastern Mediterranean and India. A third example is the horse-drawn chariot, which may have first appeared in the Inner Eurasian steppes and within less than a thousand years spread all across Eurasia from western Europe to China.There were numerous scientific, technological, and cultural innovations that complex societies achieved. To take just one early example, the city-dwellers of Sumer in southern Mesopotamia, which is as far as we know the earliest urban civilization, made fundamental scientific and technical breakthroughs in the fourth and third millennia BC. Sometime before 3000 BC, Sumerian scribes worked out a system of numerical notation in the writing script they used, called cuneiform. They used a combination of base-ten and base-sixty mathematics, together with a growing understanding of geometry, for everyday government and commerce, as well as to survey land, chart the stars, design buildings, and build irrigation works. Other technical innovations included the seed drill (a sowing device), the vaulted arch, refinements in bronze metallurgy, and, most ingenious of all, the wheel. This concept was probably first applied to pottery making, later to transport and ploughing.Within complex societies, such as those that emerged in the great river valleys, the interchange of information and ideas tended to be so intense that each society developed a distinct cultural style. We can tell apart these distinctive styles today in the surviving remnants of buildings, art objects, written texts, tools, and other material remains.
We should, however, keep two ideas in mind. One is that all complex societies were invariably changing, rather than possessing timeless, static cultural traits. The style of a civilization changed from one generation to the next because cultural expressions and values were invariably bound up with the natural environment, economic life, and politics, which were continuously changing as well. The second point is that early civilizations were not culturally self-contained. All of them developed and changed as they did partly because of their connections to other societies near and far, connections that played themselves out in trade, migration, war, and cultural exchange. |<br><img src="https://www.worldhistory.org/img/r/p/1500x1500/17844.png.webp?v=1737009437-1695055322" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/iv.-cities-and-civilisations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/IV. Cities and Civilisations.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 09:49:44 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.britannica.com/08/150008-050-D5A45539/Ziggurat-Ur.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.britannica.com/08/150008-050-D5A45539/Ziggurat-Ur.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[03 Antiquity Timelines]]></title><link>001-techniques/timelines/03-antiquity-timelines.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Timelines/03 Antiquity Timelines.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 09:47:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[II. Neolithicization, or Mesolithic-Neolithic transition]]></title><description><![CDATA[Reading tasks mark/highlight important words and concepts
define the words (monolingual dictionary)
translate only if absolutely necessary!
→ help each other, feel free to quietly discuss in pairs!
integrate text and flowcharts! Are there differences? Definitions
Mesolithic: meso: middle. lithos: stone.
Neolithic: neo: new/young.
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="02 Periods of World History > Commonly Used Western European Periods" data-href="02 Periods of World History#Commonly Used Western European Periods" href="001-techniques/timelines/02-periods-of-world-history.html#Commonly Used Western European Periods" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Timeline of Prehistory</a>
Dates
~70 000 – 10 000 BC
Ice-Ages impede spread of humans in Europe, Northern Asia and North America
~31 900 years ago
Modern humans live in South-Eastern Europe
~13 000 BC
Earliest settlements in North America. Presumably via Bering strait and Alaska from Siberia
~9000
First sheep-herding (Mesopotamia)
First use of non-regional crops (North Syria)
First Ceramics in China
~8000
First domestication of the pig (Asia)
~7000
Agriculture in Middle and South America
~5500
First domestication of the horse
~5400
First farmers come to
Middle Europe
~4500
First usage of plough (Mesopotamia)
~3200
Maize/corn becomes most important staple food in South America
Scholars generally agree that foragers (hunter-gatherers) of the Paleolithic enjoyed, at least much of the time, sufficient food supplies, adequate shelter, and shorter daily working hours than most adults do today. Humans did not, therefore, consciously take up crop growing and animal raising because they thought they would have a more secure and satisfying life. In other words, humans seem to have been “pushed” into agriculture rather than “pulled” into it.The coming of agrarian societies was almost certainly connected to the waning of the Pleistocene, or Ice Age, that is, the period, beginning about 15 000 years ago, when glaciers shrank and both sea levels and global temperatures rose. In several parts of the Northern Hemisphere rainfall increased significantly. Rising seas drowned low-lying coastal shelves as well as land bridges that had previously connected regions separated by water today. Land bridges now under water included spans between Siberia and Alaska, Australia and Papua New Guinea, and Britain and continental Europe.
One consequence of the great thaw was that across much of the Northern Hemisphere warmer, rainier, ice-free conditions permitted forests, meadowlands, and small animal populations to flourish. The natural bounty was so great in some localities that human bands began to settle in one place all or part of the year to forage and hunt. That is, they became sedentary, settled in hamlets or villages rather than moving from camp to camp. For example, in the relatively well-watered part of the Middle East we call the Fertile Crescent, groups began sometime between 10 000 and 13 000 years ago to found tiny settlements in order to collect plentiful stands of wild grain and other edible plants and animals.<br>The Fertile Crescent
<img alt="Fertile Crescent" src="https://cdn.britannica.com/50/64950-050-7FF76F71/cities-records-rivers-mouths-Euphrates-Tigris-countries.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
<br>In time, these groups learned how to control and manipulate the reproduction of plants that were bigger, tastier, more nutritious, and easier to grow, harvest, store, and cook than were wild food plants. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="I. Farming and the Emergence of Complex Societies > Animal Domestication and its Effects" data-href="I. Farming and the Emergence of Complex Societies#Animal Domestication and its Effects" href="102-early-civilisations/i.-farming-and-the-emergence-of-complex-societies.html#Animal Domestication and its Effects" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Systematic domestication</a> was under way!
In the Fertile Crescent key domesticates included the ancestors of wheat, barley, rye, and several other edible plants. Selecting and breeding particular animals species – sheep, goats, cattle, pigs – that were good to eat and easy to manage occurred in a similar way. In effect, humans started grooming the natural environment to reduce the organisms they did not want (weeds, predatory wolves) and to increase the number of organisms they did want (grains, legumes, wool-bearing sheep, hunting dogs).The intensification in population densities and economic productivity that farming permitted also led humans to intervene in the natural and physical environment as never before. As farmers cleared more land, planted more crops, and pastured more animals, they enhanced their species’ biological success. That is, there occurred a positive feedback cycle of ever-increasing population and productivity.
Beginning about 6000 BC, this intensification in particular parts of the world moved to a level that required radical innovations in the way humans lived and worked. |<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://www.wolrdhistoryforusall.sds.edu" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://www.wolrdhistoryforusall.sds.edu" target="_self">www.wolrdhistoryforusall.sds.edu</a> (adapted and shortened by RöM)after reading Sum up the factors that made sedentary lifestyle possible!
Define: pull factor / push factors
How did humans influence their environment, and how were they influenced by their own development? <br>Linear Pottery culture (5500–4500 BC)
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/68/Halle_%28Saale%29%2C_Landesmuseum_f%C3%BCr_Vorgeschichte%2C_gro%C3%9Fer_Kumpf.jpg/1257px-Halle_%28Saale%29%2C_Landesmuseum_f%C3%BCr_Vorgeschichte%2C_gro%C3%9Fer_Kumpf.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
<br>Bell-Beaker culture (2800–1800BC)
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/04/Beaker_2.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
<br>Megalith Culture <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/cc/Mane_Rethual_bei_Locmariaquer%2C_Morbihan_1.jpg/1440px-Mane_Rethual_bei_Locmariaquer%2C_Morbihan_1.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved"><br>
Dolmen du Mané-Rutual (Carnac)
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/0f/Stonehenge%2C_Salisbury_retouched.jpg/1582px-Stonehenge%2C_Salisbury_retouched.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Stone Circle at Stonehenge (from around 3000 BC)
]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/ii.-neolithicization,-or-mesolithic-neolithic-transition.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/II. Neolithicization, or Mesolithic-Neolithic transition.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 09:03:49 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.britannica.com/50/64950-050-7FF76F71/cities-records-rivers-mouths-Euphrates-Tigris-countries.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.britannica.com/50/64950-050-7FF76F71/cities-records-rivers-mouths-Euphrates-Tigris-countries.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[02 Periods of World History]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img alt="Pasted image 20250626082047.png" src="001-techniques/timelines/pasted-image-20250626082047.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>001-techniques/timelines/02-periods-of-world-history.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Timelines/02 Periods of World History.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 09:00:48 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[V. Repetition chapters 101 and 102]]></title><description><![CDATA[Repetition block 1 What is history / prehistory?
What is a period / epoch?
What is domestication? When did farming start? Why did people start farming?
How did humans influence their environment, and how were they influenced by their own development? Repetition block 2 Repeat and sum up the features of early civilizations
Social customs and institutions changed greatly with the formation of early complex societies. Describe general characteristics of complex societies
How do you expect the personal lifestyle of an individual or a family to have changed from a nomadic to a sedentary lifestyle in an early city (speculate!) How did religions support the development of early complex societies? – What other fictions do you think played (and still play) important roles in societies?
What role does constant change play in (early) societies? ]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/v.-repetition-chapters-101-and-102.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/V. Repetition chapters 101 and 102.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 14:24:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[Marcel Röthlisberger
Gymnasium Lerbermatt
©MMXXV]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 13:59:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[IV. Repetition chapters 101 and 102]]></title><description><![CDATA[Repetition What is history / prehistory?
What is a period / epoch?
What is domestication? When did farming start? Why did people start farming?
How did humans influence their environment, and how were they influenced by their own development? ]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/iv.-repetition-chapters-101-and-102.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/IV. Repetition chapters 101 and 102.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 13:56:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[I. Farming and the Emergence of Complex Societies]]></title><description><![CDATA[What is farming?
how did people provide for food before farming?
Flowcharts
Try to understand what is going on
formulate the processes, put them into your own words, explain them to each other
Better hunting &amp; gathering → more settled lifestyleAbility to keep and domesticate animals thatmost animals suitable for domesticationwere found exclusively in Eurasiaand especially the fertile crescentanimalsherd animals' diseases often infect humans→ Eurasian civilisations adapt→ advantages vs. cultures not previously exposedchronic clashes throughout historybetween nomads grazing their herds in dry grasslandsand settled farmers in well watered areasare herbivorousand fast-growinglive in herds with strictsocial hierarchy that humans can take overare tame and willingto breed in captivitySheep &amp; goats (c. 8000 BC) → easily tamed →Pigs (c. 7000 BC) that scavenge →Cows (c. 6500 BC) - hard to tame, but:Horses (c. 3000 BC) when tamed and bred up in size:meat &amp; milk for foodcan digest cellulose → make hilly land usefulwool for clothingreduce wasteNeed less supervisioncheap to keepdigest cellulosepull plows → more farmlandgive hides, meat &amp; milknew source of energyfaster communication→bigger empiresmore mobile armies Recompilebetter hunting and gathering technology (sickles, baskets)EffectsWhy in Eurasia?Warmer, wetter climate (c. 10.000 BC) →Wild grains spread in Middle EastEurasia's East-West axis: plants share same climate and seasonal variations of sunlightDomestic crops and intensive agriculture can spread rapidly from one centerAgriculture develops first in Fertile Crescent becauseCities and civilisations can develop and spread rapidly from one centerPermanent villages with stable grain supplies which allowRising population →Need more food, but won't abandon easier hunter-gatherer lifestyle →Casual agriculture mixed withhunting and gatheringIntensificationEventually settle down to full-time agriculture with important results:Hot dry summers → Big seeds for fast growth → No woody stems → Big nutritious grains &amp; easy harvestIt has many self pollinating cereals → Don't breed with other plants → Don't lose valued recessive traitsTime to watch seeds grow → discovery of agriculutre (8000 BC)Women don't carry kids so far→ Less need tocontrol population growthYoung children can eat grains →Women wean children earlier →Shorter gaps between pregnanciespopulation growth depletes H&amp;G resourcesNeed more food → rely more on agricultureDevelop new agricultural techniques:2-field system, crop rotation → population growsLess cooperation and sharing →Private property→social classes andmore conflict→Start of status gap between genders RecompileThe Spread of Agriculture
<img alt="Spread of Agriculture" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/e9/Centres_of_origin_and_spread_of_agriculture.svg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Map of the world showing approximate centres of origin of agriculture and its spread in prehistory: the Fertile Crescent (11,000 BP), the Yangtze and Yellow River basins (9,000 BP) and the Papua New Guinea Highlands (9,000–6,000 BP), Central Mexico (5,000–4,000 BP), Northern South America (5,000–4,000 BP), sub-Saharan Africa (5,000–4,000 BP, exact location unknown), eastern North America (4,000–3,000 BP). (BP: "before present
]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/i.-farming-and-the-emergence-of-complex-societies.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/I. Farming and the Emergence of Complex Societies.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 13:20:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/e9/Centres_of_origin_and_spread_of_agriculture.svg" length="0" type="image/svg+xml"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/e9/Centres_of_origin_and_spread_of_agriculture.svg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[II. "Civilisations and Cities"]]></title><description><![CDATA[Reading tasks mark/highlight important words and concepts
define the words (monolingual dictionary)
translate only if absolutely necessary!
→ help each other, feel free to quietly discuss in pairs!
integrate text and flowcharts! Are there differences? Timeline
~70 000 – 10 000 BC
Ice-Ages impede spread of humans in Europe, Northern Asia and North America
~31 900 years ago
Modern humans live in South-Eastern Europe
~13 000 BC
Earliest settlements in North America. Presumably via Bering strait and Alaska from Siberia
~9000
First sheep-herding (Mesopotamia)
First use of non-regional crops (North Syria)
First Ceramics in China
~8000
First domestication of the pig (Asia)
~7000
Agriculture in Middle and South America
~5500
First domestication of the horse
~5400
First farmers come to
Middle Europe
~4500
First usage of plough (Mesopotamia)
~3200
Maize/corn becomes most important staple food in South America
Scholars generally agree that foragers (hunter-gatherers) of the Paleolithic enjoyed, at least much of the time, sufficient food supplies, adequate shelter, and shorter daily working hours than most adults do today. Humans did not, therefore, consciously take up crop growing and animal raising because they thought they would have a more secure and satisfying life. In other words, humans seem to have been “pushed” into agriculture rather than “pulled” into it.The coming of agrarian societies was almost certainly connected to the waning of the Pleistocene, or Ice Age, that is, the period, beginning about 15 000 years ago, when glaciers shrank and both sea levels and global temperatures rose. In several parts of the Northern Hemisphere rainfall increased significantly. Rising seas drowned low-lying coastal shelves as well as land bridges that had previously connected regions separated by water today. Land bridges now under water included spans between Siberia and Alaska, Australia and Papua New Guinea, and Britain and continental Europe.
One consequence of the great thaw was that across much of the Northern Hemisphere warmer, rainier, ice-free conditions permitted forests, meadowlands, and small animal populations to flourish. The natural bounty was so great in some localities that human bands began to settle in one place all or part of the year to forage and hunt. That is, they became sedentary, settled in hamlets or villages rather than moving from camp to camp. For example, in the relatively well-watered part of the Middle East we call the Fertile Crescent, groups began sometime between 10 000 and 13 000 years ago to found tiny settlements in order to collect plentiful stands of wild grain and other edible plants and animals.The Fertile Crescent
<img alt="Fertile Crescent" src="https://cdn.britannica.com/50/64950-050-7FF76F71/cities-records-rivers-mouths-Euphrates-Tigris-countries.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
<br>In time, these groups learned how to control and manipulate the reproduction of plants that were bigger, tastier, more nutritious, and easier to grow, harvest, store, and cook than were wild food plants. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="I. Farming and the Emergence of Complex Societies > Animal Domestication and its Effects" data-href="I. Farming and the Emergence of Complex Societies#Animal Domestication and its Effects" href="102-early-civilisations/i.-farming-and-the-emergence-of-complex-societies.html#Animal Domestication and its Effects" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Systematic domestication</a> was under way!
In the Fertile Crescent key domesticates included the ancestors of wheat, barley, rye, and several other edible plants. Selecting and breeding particular animals species – sheep, goats, cattle, pigs – that were good to eat and easy to manage occurred in a similar way. In effect, humans started grooming the natural environment to reduce the organisms they did not want (weeds, predatory wolves) and to increase the number of organisms they did want (grains, legumes, wool-bearing sheep, hunting dogs).The intensification in population densities and economic productivity that farming permitted also led humans to intervene in the natural and physical environment as never before. As farmers cleared more land, planted more crops, and pastured more animals, they enhanced their species’ biological success. That is, there occurred a positive feedback cycle of ever-increasing population and productivity.
Beginning about 6000 BC, this intensification in particular parts of the world moved to a level that required radical innovations in the way humans lived and worked.First in the Tigris-Euphrates and Nile River valleys, then the Indus valley, and later in China’s Huang River (Huang He) valley and a few other regions, societies emerged that were far larger and denser than the farming communities of the Neolithic period. We refer to these big concentrations of people as complex societies, or, more traditionally, as civilisations.
Their most noticeable characteristic was cities. Early cities were centres of power, manufacturing, and creativity. Building and preserving them, however, required drastic alterations of the local environment to produce sufficient food, building materials, and sources of energy. The price of this intervention was high. Dense urban societies were extremely vulnerable to changes in weather, climate, disease conditions, wood supplies, and trade links to distant regions. After the appearance of complex societies, humans stepped up their efforts to manipulate and control their physical and natural environment. This had great benefits but also produced a negative feedback cycle.Timeline
Among the oldest cities are
Jericho (fortified ~8000)
Çatal Hüyük (~7000)
Ur (~5000)
Byblos (5th millennium)
~5700
First proto-urban
architecture in Egypt
~5500
Neolithical settlements with long houses in Middle Europe
~4600
First city-like settlements in the Indus valley
~4300 to ~800 BC
Stilt house settlements in central Europe
~3800
Cultures in China
organized in cities
~3300
Glacier man “Ötzi”
~3100 to ~2600
Stonehenge
~3000
Sumerian city-states
~2600 – 1800
Mohenjo-Daro in the Indus valley, systematically planned city
The intensification of population and production obliged humans to experiment with new forms of social organization. The customs and rules that governed social relationships in a foraging band of twentyfive or thirty people were no longer adequate.After about 4000 BC, massive changes occur in social customs and institutions. The complex societies that arose in the Tigris-Euphrates, Nile, and Indus valleys, and somewhat later in other regions, were cauldrons of intensification. That is, people lived and worked together in much larger, denser communities than had ever existed. These societies shared a number of fundamental characteristics, which we generally associate with civilizations:
Cities arose, the early ones varying somewhat in their forms and functions. By 2250 BC, there were about eight cities in the world that had 30 000 or more inhabitants. By 1200 BC there were about sixteen cities that big.
Some people took up full-time specialized occupations and professions (artisans, merchants, soldiers, priests, and so on) rather than spending most of their time collecting, producing, or processing food.
A hierarchy of social classes (social stratification) appeared in which some men and women – the elite class – had more wealth, power, and privilege than did others. Also, men became dominant over women in political and social life, leading to patriarchy.
The state, that is, a centralized system of government and command, was invented. This meant that a minority group – kings, queens, high officials, priests, generals – exercised control over the labour and social behaviour of everyone else.
Complex exchanges of food and other products took place within the complex society, and lines of trade connected the society to neighbours near and far.
Technological innovations multiplied, and each new useful invention tended to suggest several others.
Monumental building took place – city walls, temples, palaces, public plazas, and tombs of rulers.
A system of writing, or at least a complex method of record-keeping, came into use.
Spiritual belief systems, public laws, and artistic expressions all became richer and more complex.
Creative individuals collaborated with the ruling class to lay the foundations of astronomy, mathematics, and chemistry, as well as civil engineering and architecture.
Timeline
~3000
Parallel development of cuneiform in Mesopotamia and hieroglyphs in Egypt
~2980
First unification of Upper and Lower Egypt (Old Kingdom)
~2650 – 2190
Time of the Pyramids
~2650 First step pyramid by Snofru
~2600 Cheops pyramid
2600 – ~1425
Minoan culture on Crete
~1900 – 1531
Babylonian Empire
~1700
Code of Hammurabi, earliest known law code
~1600
Mycenaean Culture,
earliest advanced civilization on mainland Europe
~1000 – 70 BC
Kingdom of Israel (with interruptions)
30 BC
Death of the last pharaoh, Cleopatra VII.
Egypt becomes a Roman province A society did not have to have every one of these characteristics to qualify as a civilization. The checklist is less important than the fact that all these social, cultural, economic, and political elements interacted dynamically with one another. The synergism among them made the society complex, that is, made it recognizable as a civilization.World population started growing at a faster rate than ever before. The size and density of communities expanded, and networks of communication by land and sea became more extensive and sophisticated. Along with these developments came, as we might well expect, an intensification in the flow of information and a general speed-up in the accumulation of knowledge of all kinds.
One example is religious knowledge. In the early millennia of this period certain ideas, practices, and artistic expressions centred on the worship of female deities spread widely along routes of trade and migration to embrace a large part of western Eurasia. Another example is the idea and technology of writing, which emerged first, as far as we know, in either Egypt or Mesopotamia and spread widely from there to the eastern Mediterranean and India. A third example is the horse-drawn chariot, which may have first appeared in the Inner Eurasian steppes and within less than a thousand years spread all across Eurasia from western Europe to China.There were numerous scientific, technological, and cultural innovations that complex societies achieved. To take just one early example, the city-dwellers of Sumer in southern Mesopotamia, which is as far as we know the earliest urban civilization, made fundamental scientific and technical breakthroughs in the fourth and third millennia BC. Sometime before 3000 BC, Sumerian scribes worked out a system of numerical notation in the writing script they used, called cuneiform. They used a combination of base-ten and base-sixty mathematics, together with a growing understanding of geometry, for everyday government and commerce, as well as to survey land, chart the stars, design buildings, and build irrigation works. Other technical innovations included the seed drill (a sowing device), the vaulted arch, refinements in bronze metallurgy, and, most ingenious of all, the wheel. This concept was probably first applied to pottery making, later to transport and ploughing.Within complex societies, such as those that emerged in the great river valleys, the interchange of information and ideas tended to be so intense that each society developed a distinct cultural style. We can tell apart these distinctive styles today in the surviving remnants of buildings, art objects, written texts, tools, and other material remains.
We should, however, keep two ideas in mind. One is that all complex societies were invariably changing, rather than possessing timeless, static cultural traits. The style of a civilization changed from one generation to the next because cultural expressions and values were invariably bound up with the natural environment, economic life, and politics, which were continuously changing as well. The second point is that early civilizations were not culturally self-contained. All of them developed and changed as they did partly because of their connections to other societies near and far, connections that played themselves out in trade, migration, war, and cultural exchange. |<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://www.wolrdhistoryforusall.sds.edu" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link is-unresolved" href="http://www.wolrdhistoryforusall.sds.edu" target="_self">www.wolrdhistoryforusall.sds.edu</a> (adapted and shortened by RöM)after reading Sum up the factors that made sedentary lifestyle possible!
Define: pull factor / push factors
How did humans influence their environment, and how were they influenced by their own development? <br>Linear Pottery culture (5500–4500 BC)
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/68/Halle_%28Saale%29%2C_Landesmuseum_f%C3%BCr_Vorgeschichte%2C_gro%C3%9Fer_Kumpf.jpg/1257px-Halle_%28Saale%29%2C_Landesmuseum_f%C3%BCr_Vorgeschichte%2C_gro%C3%9Fer_Kumpf.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
<br>Bell-Beaker culture (2800–1800BC)
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/04/Beaker_2.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
<br>Megalith Culture <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/c/cc/Mane_Rethual_bei_Locmariaquer%2C_Morbihan_1.jpg/1440px-Mane_Rethual_bei_Locmariaquer%2C_Morbihan_1.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved"><br>
Dolmen du Mané-Rutual (Carnac)
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/0/0f/Stonehenge%2C_Salisbury_retouched.jpg/1582px-Stonehenge%2C_Salisbury_retouched.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Stone Circle at Stonehenge (from around 3000 BC)
]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/ii.-"civilisations-and-cities".html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/II. "Civilisations and Cities".md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 13:20:19 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.britannica.com/50/64950-050-7FF76F71/cities-records-rivers-mouths-Euphrates-Tigris-countries.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.britannica.com/50/64950-050-7FF76F71/cities-records-rivers-mouths-Euphrates-Tigris-countries.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[negative-feedback-loop]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="102-early-civilisations/resources/negative-feedback-loop.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>102-early-civilisations/resources/negative-feedback-loop.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">102 Early Civilisations/resources/negative-feedback-loop.jpg</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 12:59:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[I. Humans and Societies]]></title><description><![CDATA[What makes us humans?
Is it upright walking? Art? Language? ...?
How do the following images illustrate and date possible indicators of "being human"?
Image
<img alt="Ardi, By Tobias Fluegel - Own work, CC BY-SA 3.0," src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/56/Ardipithecus_Gesamt.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Ardipithecus Ramidus, "Ardi". Humanoid walking upright, 4.4 million years ago
<br>Image
<img alt="Olduvai hand axe" src="https://media.britishmuseum.org/media/Repository/Documents/2014_10/11_5/64e16237_7a2a_42c1_9ea4_a3c10053a77c/mid_00602458_001.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Hand axe found in the Olduvai gorge, Tanzania, ~1.2 million years old. British Museum
<br>Image
<img alt="Chauvet cave paintings" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0d/Chauvet%C2%B4s_cave_horses.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Cave paintings in the cave of Chauvet, Ardèche, Southern France, 32.000–35.000 years old.
<br>Image
<img alt="Vogelherdpferd" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6c/Pferd_Vogelherd_Kopie.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Wild horse made of mammoth ivory, 32.000 years old, 4.8 cm long, Vogelherd cave, Schwäbische Alb, Germany
<br>Image
<img alt="Venus von Willendorf" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f7/Willendorf-Venus-1468.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
"Venus of Willendorf", a female figurine, limestone, 11 cm, Willendorf, Germany, c. 29.000 years old
People made art. What can this tell us about them and their society?
What do people need in order to be able to make art?
What does a society need to look like if people in it can make art?
<br><img alt="Pasted image 20250812120735.png" src="101-prehistory/resources/pasted-image-20250812120735.png" target="_self">
cooperation
myths <br><img alt="map-of-early-human-migrations-6605.png" src="101-prehistory/resources/map-of-early-human-migrations-6605.png" target="_self"><br><img alt="Neolithic-Revolution-comic.jpg" src="101-prehistory/resources/neolithic-revolution-comic.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>101-prehistory/i.-humans-and-societies.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">101 Prehistory/I. Humans and Societies.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 12:55:48 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/56/Ardipithecus_Gesamt.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/56/Ardipithecus_Gesamt.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[map-of-early-human-migrations-6605]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="101-prehistory/resources/map-of-early-human-migrations-6605.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>101-prehistory/resources/map-of-early-human-migrations-6605.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">101 Prehistory/resources/map-of-early-human-migrations-6605.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 12:54:09 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Neolithic-Revolution-comic]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="101-prehistory/resources/neolithic-revolution-comic.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>101-prehistory/resources/neolithic-revolution-comic.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">101 Prehistory/resources/Neolithic-Revolution-comic.jpg</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 12:52:32 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250812120735]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="101-prehistory/resources/pasted-image-20250812120735.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>101-prehistory/resources/pasted-image-20250812120735.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">101 Prehistory/resources/Pasted image 20250812120735.png</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 10:07:35 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to Learn About the Past]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img alt="Pasted image 20250626073926.png" src="001-techniques/sources/resources/pasted-image-20250626073926.png" target="_self"><br><img alt="Pasted image 20250626074021.png" src="001-techniques/sources/resources/pasted-image-20250626074021.png" target="_self">
Cuneiform, Mesopotamia<br><img alt="Hieroglyps, Egypt" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c9/Hieroglyphs_from_the_tomb_of_Seti_I.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer" target="_self" class="is-unresolved">
Hieroglyphs, EgyptThink/Discuss: What is History?
Define and separate from prehistory
]]></description><link>001-techniques/sources/how-to-learn-about-the-past.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Sources/How to Learn About the Past.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 12:20:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[01 Timelines - Overview]]></title><description><![CDATA[Showing the passage of time, events, structures, etc. in the form of a timeline provides visual information for something which is hard to grasp, quite abstract and arbitrary.
The first timelines appeared in the time of enlightenment, when scholars started to assemble vast amounts of data and felt a strong need to organise and order this data.How do we define that something is “antique” or “medieval”?
→ Time frames: Periods
How could periods be defined?
Definition: A period is a stretch of time with relatively stable characteristics in arts and architecture, material use, human lifestyle, political systems, etc.
]]></description><link>001-techniques/timelines/01-timelines-overview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Timelines/01 Timelines - Overview.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 10:05:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250626082437]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="001-techniques/timelines/pasted-image-20250626082437.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>001-techniques/timelines/pasted-image-20250626082437.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Timelines/Pasted image 20250626082437.png</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 06:24:37 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250626082047]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="001-techniques/timelines/pasted-image-20250626082047.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>001-techniques/timelines/pasted-image-20250626082047.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Timelines/Pasted image 20250626082047.png</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 06:20:47 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250626074021]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="001-techniques/sources/resources/pasted-image-20250626074021.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>001-techniques/sources/resources/pasted-image-20250626074021.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Sources/resources/Pasted image 20250626074021.png</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 05:40:21 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pasted image 20250626073926]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="001-techniques/sources/resources/pasted-image-20250626073926.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>001-techniques/sources/resources/pasted-image-20250626073926.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">001 Techniques/Sources/resources/Pasted image 20250626073926.png</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 05:39:26 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>