<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[School]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>School</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 10:02:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 10:02:18 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[How seaweed is a powerful, yet surprising, climate solution]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:SeaweedApothecary" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#SeaweedApothecary</a> 
 A chance encounter on a rocky seashore led one professor to invent autonomous robotics that can harvest the power of seaweed.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym2/how-seaweed-is-a-powerful,-yet-surprising,-climate-solution.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM2/How seaweed is a powerful, yet surprising, climate solution.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Allen]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 10:02:10 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/656393/original/file-20250319-56-qh7vup.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/656393/original/file-20250319-56-qh7vup.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Seaweed is high in vitamins and minerals – but that’s not the only reason westerners should eat more of it]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 Seaweed has been eaten in some countries for years, but consumption is generally low.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym2/seaweed-is-high-in-vitamins-and-minerals-–-but-that’s-not-the-only-reason-westerners-should-eat-more-of-it.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM2/Seaweed is high in vitamins and minerals – but that’s not the only reason westerners should eat more of it.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Wilkinson,Rochelle Embling]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 06:58:21 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://cdn.theconversation.com/avatars/1158702/width238/file-20200921-18-1tx2udz.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.theconversation.com/avatars/1158702/width238/file-20200921-18-1tx2udz.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[What a 19th-century atlas teaches me about marine ecosystems]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 Historical maps and records from across Europe show just how much oyster beds and other marine habitats have changed over the centuries.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym2/what-a-19th-century-atlas-teaches-me-about-marine-ecosystems.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM2/What a 19th-century atlas teaches me about marine ecosystems.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Ruth H. Thurstan]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 08:39:35 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/663154/original/file-20250422-68-unf8yw.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/663154/original/file-20250422-68-unf8yw.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How farming could change in a post-growth world]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><img alt="Pipes serving as growing facilities on a rooftop" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/579171/original/file-20240301-26-k3hnmb.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/profiles/handan-vicdan-953671" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/handan-vicdan-953671" target="_blank">Handan Vicdan</a> Published: May 22, 2024 4.58pm BST<br>Degrowth, or the idea that we can save the planet by shrinking our economies, is ceasing to be a fringe concept. In the past years, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/france/article/2022/10/24/degrowth-a-policy-that-divides-environmentalists_6001503_7.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/france/article/2022/10/24/degrowth-a-policy-that-divides-environmentalists_6001503_7.html" target="_blank">green politicians across the EU</a> have increasingly claimed the school of thought offers the best solution to the ecological crisis.<br>In some quarters, science is also lending its credentials: the United Nations’ scientific panels tasked with measuring climate breakdown and biodiversity loss, the IPCC and IPBES, have respectively suggested governments consider <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-04412-x" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-04412-x" target="_blank">degrowth policies</a> to fight ecological breakdown, while academics are now incorporating <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/opinion/article/2024/04/26/climate-change-no-scientific-models-included-any-hypotheses-of-degrowth-until-very-recently_6669596_23.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/opinion/article/2024/04/26/climate-change-no-scientific-models-included-any-hypotheses-of-degrowth-until-very-recently_6669596_23.html" target="_blank">degrowth scenarios in scientific models</a>.<br><br>What these concepts would look like in real life, however, is still a work in progress. As a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://em-lyon.com/en/handan-vicdan/briefly" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://em-lyon.com/en/handan-vicdan/briefly" target="_blank">scholar researching technology use in alternative markets</a>, I have been particularly interested in exploring degrowth’s relationship to technology.<br>Contrary to common perceptions, degrowthers are not against technology. In fact, some of the school’s leading thinkers such as Jason Hickel have made a point of rejecting the label of “anti-technology”, stressing that the movement prioritises changes and efficiency improvements to the extent that they are <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://monthlyreview.org/2023/07/01/on-technology-and-degrowth/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://monthlyreview.org/2023/07/01/on-technology-and-degrowth/" target="_blank">“empirically feasible, ecologically coherent, and socially just”</a>. Again, what technologies may qualify according to this criteria remains to be seen. In my research, I argue that <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/14705931231199962?icid=int.sj-full-text.citing-articles.2" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/14705931231199962?icid=int.sj-full-text.citing-articles.2" target="_blank">vertical farming</a>, the practice of growing crops in stacked pots within tower-like structures on rooftops or vacant spaces, provides us with a textbook example of degrowth-friendly technology.<br>A glance at the academic literature on degrowth appears to support this. In an <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41893-022-00933-5" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41893-022-00933-5" target="_blank">article reviewing sustainable agri-food systems</a>, degrowthers celebrate “edible urban commons”<a data-footref="1" href="about:blank#fn-1-4fa04a5359ad35b0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a> and the principles of sufficiency and regeneration. In contrast to indoor vertical farms built by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.aerofarms.com/about-us/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.aerofarms.com/about-us/" target="_blank">tech giants</a>, urban rooftop farms aren’t energy intensive. By enabling individuals and small businesses to grow food outdoors in urban areas, they reduce both city dwellers’ need to grow food in the countryside and their dependency on an increasingly fickle global food-supply chain.<br><br>At heart a farmer’s nation, France offers some of the world’s most compelling examples of vertical farming. Located on the rooftop of Paris Expo’s Pavillon 6, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nu-paris.com/notre-ferme/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nu-paris.com/notre-ferme/" target="_blank">Nature Urbaine</a> is the largest urban farm in Europe with 14,000 m2 of space converted into a vertical farm. By using up every centimetre, carefully thought-out technologies allow residents to multiply the surface’s production capacity sixfold. Hundreds of towers hold fruits and vegetables suspended in the air and their roots are misted periodically with a nutrient solution. Rain gutters are also used, showering the roots with a mixture of water and nutrients.<br>While raising awareness over where our food comes from, these technologies bring locals closer to one another and enable them to exchange know-how on growing their own food. Nature Urbaine organises educational workshops for individuals, communities, and local businesses on urban food growing and environmental stewardship.<br><br>Initiated in 2016, the Dutch project <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://regenvillages.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://regenvillages.com/" target="_blank">ReGenVillages</a> aspires to create eco-villages around the world that are self-sufficient in energy and food.<br>To make them as affordable as possible, planners intend to offer <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://ec.europa.eu/enrd/sites/enrd/files/regenvillages_su_deck_overview_brief.pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://ec.europa.eu/enrd/sites/enrd/files/regenvillages_su_deck_overview_brief.pdf" target="_blank">prefabricated housing</a>. RegenVillages’ patented machine-learning software, VillageOS, aims to help residents better manage resources by providing them with data on their communities’ energy use, waste, water, and food-growing practices. This data is then sent to the cloud through which communities in similar or different climate zones can learn from each other’s management and regenerative practices.<br>Currently at the conceptual stage, the project <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://architizer.com/projects/farmhouse-7/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://architizer.com/projects/farmhouse-7/" target="_blank">Farmhouse</a> by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.precht.at/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.precht.at/" target="_blank">Austrian architecture firm Precht</a> also aims to reconnect architecture and agriculture through prefabricated structures. At first glance, its model building resembles a carefully balanced jenga game, with triangular flats alternating with cells clad with greenery. The life cycle of residents, buildings and crops support one another: emanating heat allows plants like potatoes, nuts or beans to grow. A water treatment system filters rain and greywater, enriches it with nutrients and cycles it back to the greenhouses. The food waste can be locally collected in the buildings basement, turned into compost and reused to grow more food.<br>Vertical farming technologies present in Farmhouse, Nature Urbaine or ReGenvillages give nature and soil, which we have been degrading through intensive industrial agriculture, a chance to rejuvenate. Indeed, if grown via urban farming, the environmental impact of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-023-00023-3" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-023-00023-3" target="_blank">carbon-intensive plants</a> can be reduced.<br>On top of freeing up space, these <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://sciendo.com/article/10.1515/jlecol-2017-0016" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://sciendo.com/article/10.1515/jlecol-2017-0016" target="_blank">technologies</a> help reduce our dependence on resources such as water, energy, soil, and chemicals that are necessary for intensive agricultural production. They also increase the quality of the air we breathe, creating green havens for better <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fsufs.2022.826437/full" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fsufs.2022.826437/full" target="_blank">thermal regulation</a> in cities threatened with turning into ovens over the summer.<br><br>Nonetheless, urban agriculture’s carbon footprint is a lasting concern. A serving of fruits and vegetables grown from urban agriculture emits the equivalent of 420g of carbon dioxide, six times more carbon emissions than conventional agriculture (70g CO2 equivalent). Conversely, urban agriculture outruns conventional agriculture when it comes to producing crops such as tomatoes that are less carbon intensive, and also urban farms and individually managed gardens. What remains critical is the use of less energy-intensive technologies and more climate-friendly crops in urban farms.<br>Whether we can scale these technologies to feed urban residents all over the world remains to be seen, due to small quantity and limited range food supply. However, the Covid-19 pandemic has shown the importance of local food sufficiency, as global food supply chains failed to cater to the needs of urban people.<br>Another point of contention is whether these technologies can be inclusive enough to help people from disadvantaged backgrounds to grow their own food. We can draw hope from a number of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://upfarming.org/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://upfarming.org/" target="_blank">vertical farming projects by NGOs</a>, with some coaching prison inmates and guards to grow and share their own food. These are encouraging local solidarity initiatives toward an equitable food system.<br>Finally, let’s not forget the issue of city-dwellers’ time constraints and lack of agricultural skills. Encouraging urban people to grow food will require substantial societal transformations to blend work and personal life. For example, shared corporate gardens and degrowth labour policy proposals such as the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://grist.org/looking-forward/its-not-just-you-the-planet-wants-a-4-day-workweek-too/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://grist.org/looking-forward/its-not-just-you-the-planet-wants-a-4-day-workweek-too/" target="_blank">four-day working week</a> could enable more people to invest time in learning to grow their own food with their communities. |<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/how-farming-could-change-in-a-post-growth-world-224465" target="_blank">https://theconversation.com/how-farming-could-change-in-a-post-growth-world-224465</a> (12. February 2025)<br><br><br><br>Answer the following questions in 3-5 sentences each. Use your own words as far as possible. Do not copy from the text.<br>
<br>In your own words, describe 3 of the techniques used in the Nature Urbaine project and the Framhouse project.
<br>Name and explain 4 important positive effects of vertical urban farming.
<br>Speculate why the CO2 output of urban farming is higher than that of conventional farming. What could be done to reduce this aspect?
<br><br>Tick T for true or F for false. Give around 2-3 sentences to indicate where you find this in the text.<br>
<br>
People who criticise economical growth are also mostly against technological progress.<br>
[ ] T [ ] F → evidence in the text?

<br>
All the projects desribed in the text are up and running.<br>
[ ] T [ ] F → evidence in the text?

<br>
Urban farming can help regenerate farmlands.<br>
​[ ] T [ ] F → evidence in the text?

<br>
The authors of the study think that urban vertical farming is easy to do for an urban population.<br>
​[ ] T [ ] F → evidence in the text?

<br>
<br>
<br>“Commons” refers to the (medieval) concept of communally owned and managed lands.<a href="about:blank#fnref-1-4fa04a5359ad35b0" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/how-farming-could-change-in-a-post-growth-world.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/How farming could change in a post-growth world.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Handan Vincan]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 12:39:51 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/579171/original/file-20240301-26-k3hnmb.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/579171/original/file-20240301-26-k3hnmb.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How farming could change in a post-growth world]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/profiles/handan-vicdan-953671" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/handan-vicdan-953671" target="_blank">Handan Vicdan </a>Published: May 22, 2024 5.58pm CEST<br>Degrowth, or the idea that we can save the planet by shrinking our economies, is ceasing to be a fringe concept. In the past years, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/france/article/2022/10/24/degrowth-a-policy-that-divides-environmentalists_6001503_7.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/france/article/2022/10/24/degrowth-a-policy-that-divides-environmentalists_6001503_7.html" target="_blank">green politicians across the EU</a> have increasingly claimed the school of thought offers the best solution to the ecological crisis.<br>In some quarters, science is also lending its credentials: the United Nations’ scientific panels tasked with measuring climate breakdown and biodiversity loss, the IPCC and IPBES, have respectively suggested governments consider <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-04412-x" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-04412-x" target="_blank">degrowth policies</a> to fight ecological breakdown, while academics are now incorporating <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/opinion/article/2024/04/26/climate-change-no-scientific-models-included-any-hypotheses-of-degrowth-until-very-recently_6669596_23.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/opinion/article/2024/04/26/climate-change-no-scientific-models-included-any-hypotheses-of-degrowth-until-very-recently_6669596_23.html" target="_blank">degrowth scenarios in scientific models</a>.<br><br>What these concepts would look like in real life, however, is still a work in progress. As a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://em-lyon.com/en/handan-vicdan/briefly" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://em-lyon.com/en/handan-vicdan/briefly" target="_blank">scholar researching technology use in alternative markets</a>, I have been particularly interested in exploring degrowth’s relationship to technology.<br>Contrary to common perceptions, degrowthers are not against technology. In fact, some of the school’s leading thinkers such as Jason Hickel have made a point of rejecting the label of “anti-technology”, stressing that the movement prioritises changes and efficiency improvements to the extent that they are <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://monthlyreview.org/2023/07/01/on-technology-and-degrowth/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://monthlyreview.org/2023/07/01/on-technology-and-degrowth/" target="_blank">“empirically feasible, ecologically coherent, and socially just”</a>. Again, what technologies may qualify according to this criteria remains to be seen. In my research, I argue that <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/14705931231199962?icid=int.sj-full-text.citing-articles.2" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/14705931231199962?icid=int.sj-full-text.citing-articles.2" target="_blank">vertical farming</a>, the practice of growing crops in stacked pots within tower-like structures on rooftops or vacant spaces, provides us with a textbook example of degrowth-friendly technology.<br>A glance at the academic literature on degrowth appears to support this. In an <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41893-022-00933-5" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41893-022-00933-5" target="_blank">article reviewing sustainable agri-food systems</a>, degrowthers celebrate “edible urban commons” and the principles of sufficiency and regeneration. In contrast to indoor vertical farms built by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.aerofarms.com/about-us/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.aerofarms.com/about-us/" target="_blank">tech giants</a>, urban rooftop farms aren’t energy intensive. By enabling individuals and small businesses to grow food outdoors in urban areas, they reduce both city dwellers’ need to grow food in the countryside and their dependency on an increasingly fickle global food-supply chain.<br><br>At heart a farmer’s nation, France offers some of the world’s most compelling examples of vertical farming. Located on the rooftop of Paris Expo’s Pavillon 6, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nu-paris.com/notre-ferme/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nu-paris.com/notre-ferme/" target="_blank">Nature Urbaine</a> is the largest urban farm in Europe with 14,000 m2 of space converted into a vertical farm. By using up every centimetre, carefully thought-out technologies allow residents to multiply the surface’s production capacity sixfold. Hundreds of towers hold fruits and vegetables suspended in the air and their roots are misted periodically with a nutrient solution. Rain gutters are also used, showering the roots with a mixture of water and nutrients.<br>While raising awareness over where our food comes from, these technologies bring locals closer to one another and enable them to exchange know-how on growing their own food. Nature Urbaine organises educational workshops for individuals, communities, and local businesses on urban food growing and environmental stewardship.<br><br>Initiated in 2016, the Dutch project <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://regenvillages.com/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://regenvillages.com/" target="_blank">ReGenVillages</a> aspires to create eco-villages around the world that are self-sufficient in energy and food.<br>To make them as affordable as possible, planners intend to offer <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://ec.europa.eu/enrd/sites/enrd/files/regenvillages_su_deck_overview_brief.pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://ec.europa.eu/enrd/sites/enrd/files/regenvillages_su_deck_overview_brief.pdf" target="_blank">prefabricated housing</a>. RegenVillages’ patented machine-learning software, VillageOS, aims to help residents better manage resources by providing them with data on their communities’ energy use, waste, water, and food-growing practices. This data is then sent to the cloud through which communities in similar or different climate zones can learn from each other’s management and regenerative practices.<br>Currently at the conceptual stage, the project <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://architizer.com/projects/farmhouse-7/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://architizer.com/projects/farmhouse-7/" target="_blank">Farmhouse</a> by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.precht.at/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.precht.at/" target="_blank">Austrian architecture firm Precht</a> also aims to reconnect architecture and agriculture through prefabricated structures. At first glance, its model building resembles a carefully balanced jenga game, with triangular flats alternating with cells clad with greenery. The life cycle of residents, buildings and crops support one another: emanating heat allows plants like potatoes, nuts or beans to grow. A water treatment system filters rain and greywater, enriches it with nutrients and cycles it back to the greenhouses. The food waste can be locally collected in the buildings basement, turned into compost and reused to grow more food.<br>Vertical farming technologies present in Farmhouse, Nature Urbaine or ReGenvillages give nature and soil, which we have been degrading through intensive industrial agriculture, a chance to rejuvenate. Indeed, if grown via urban farming, the environmental impact of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-023-00023-3" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s44284-023-00023-3" target="_blank">carbon-intensive plants</a> can be reduced.<br>On top of freeing up space, these <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://sciendo.com/article/10.1515/jlecol-2017-0016" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://sciendo.com/article/10.1515/jlecol-2017-0016" target="_blank">technologies</a> help reduce our dependence on resources such as water, energy, soil, and chemicals that are necessary for intensive agricultural production. They also increase the quality of the air we breathe, creating green havens for better <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fsufs.2022.826437/full" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fsufs.2022.826437/full" target="_blank">thermal regulation</a> in cities threatened with turning into ovens over the summer.<br><br>Nonetheless, urban agriculture’s carbon footprint is a lasting concern. A serving of fruits and vegetables grown from urban agriculture emits the equivalent of 420g of carbon dioxide, six times more carbon emissions than conventional agriculture (70g CO2 equivalent). Conversely, urban agriculture outruns conventional agriculture when it comes to producing crops such as tomatoes that are less carbon intensive, and also urban farms and individually managed gardens. What remains critical is the use of less energy-intensive technologies and more climate-friendly crops in urban farms.<br>Whether we can scale these technologies to feed urban residents all over the world remains to be seen, due to small quantity and limited range food supply. However, the Covid-19 pandemic has shown the importance of local food sufficiency, as global food supply chains failed to cater to the needs of urban people.<br>Another point of contention is whether these technologies can be inclusive enough to help people from disadvantaged backgrounds to grow their own food. We can draw hope from a number of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://upfarming.org/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://upfarming.org/" target="_blank">vertical farming projects by NGOs</a>, with some coaching prison inmates and guards to grow and share their own food. These are encouraging local solidarity initiatives toward an equitable food system.<br>Finally, let’s not forget the issue of city-dwellers’ time constraints and lack of agricultural skills. Encouraging urban people to grow food will require substantial societal transformations to blend work and personal life. For example, shared corporate gardens and degrowth labour policy proposals such as the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://grist.org/looking-forward/its-not-just-you-the-planet-wants-a-4-day-workweek-too/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://grist.org/looking-forward/its-not-just-you-the-planet-wants-a-4-day-workweek-too/" target="_blank">four-day working week</a> could enable more people to invest time in learning to grow their own food with their communities.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/how-farming-in-a-post-growth-world.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/How Farming in a post-growth world.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 16:22:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How the buildings – Questions]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>burgeoning<br>
a) stagnating<br>
b) vanishing<br>
c) growing rapidly<br>
d) decreasing
<br>far-reaching<br>
a) having a broad impact<br>
b) wide-going<br>
c) local<br>
d) coming from abroad
<br>lend an urgency<br>
a) create a sense of immediacy<br>
b) stir up the situation<br>
c) decrease the importance<br>
d) Make it less relevant
<br>vulnerable groups<br>
a) at-risk populations<br>
b) wealthy individuals<br>
c) powerful organizations<br>
d) government agencies
<br>impair decision-making processes<br>
a) facilitate discussions<br>
b) encourage indecision<br>
c) improve clarity<br>
d) hinder the ability to make choices
<br>visually monotonous<br>
a) intricately designed<br>
b) dynamically appealing<br>
c) colorful<br>
d) lacking visual variety
<br>interchangeable architectural landscapes<br>
a) cultural heritage sites<br>
b) similar building environments<br>
c) unique structures<br>
d) indigenous designs
<br>elevate stress levels<br>
a) develop calm<br>
b) induce pressure<br>
c) increase anxiety<br>
d) enhance relaxation
<br>distinctive features<br>
a) generic traits<br>
b) common elements<br>
c) ordinary aspects<br>
d) unique characteristics
<br>spatial stressors<br>
a) relaxing spaces<br>
b) environmental factors causing stress<br>
c) outdoor features<br>
d) recreational areas
<br>ongoing exposure<br>
a) sporadic appearance<br>
b) continuous contact<br>
c) infrequent interaction<br>
d) temporary presence
<br>tentative evidence<br>
a) solid facts<br>
b) preliminary proof<br>
c) conclusive findings<br>
d) strong assertions
<br>biophilic<br>
a) hostile to living things<br>
b) design approach connecting humans with nature<br>
c) technologically innovative<br>
d) exclamation, contraction of “by our Philip”
<br>mitigate<br>
a) worsen<br>
b) ignore<br>
c) intensify<br>
d) reduce the severity
<br>pivotal shift<br>
a) constant state<br>
b) significant change<br>
c) minor adjustment<br>
d) unrelated transformation
<br><br>Stay with the information you get in the text!<br>
<br>Explain in your own words, what the field of neuroarchitecture is and what it studies.
<br>There's an explanation offered as to why chronic stress and neuroinflammation appear more often in cities. Explain!
<br>What do the authors suggest is the problem with school buildings nowadays, and how should this be addressed in the future?
]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/how-the-buildings-–-questions.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/How the buildings – Questions.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 07:02:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How the buildings you occupy might be affecting your brain]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Cleo Valentine, Heather Mitcheltree, published on PSYCHE on 2 September 2024<br>Cutting-edge research in the field of neuroarchitecture is revealing the public health implications of building design<br><img src="https://images.aeonmedia.co/images/3ecb8e58-5348-4eb5-a791-cf87164f250c/rt-nest-perkins-and-will.jpg?top=4&amp;left=0&amp;cropWidth=1936&amp;cropHeight=1089&amp;width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Have you ever experienced a space that made you feel uneasy or stressed? Perhaps it was a noisy and crowded shopping mall, with its neon signs, patterned tilework and boldly painted walls in franchise signature colours. Or the poorly lit work carpark with flickering fluorescent lighting, low ceilings and hard concrete surfaces that made your every footstep echo. Now contrast that experience with a space that made you feel at ease. It might have been that time you were sitting at the table in your friend’s kitchen – the sun coming in through the window, warming your skin and filling the space with light; the smell of fresh coffee brewing; and the first blush of colour in the buds of the pot plants on the windowsill. Or maybe it was sitting in your favourite spot at the local library – the comfy seat in the quiet area with the high ceilings, ample natural light and a view out over the courtyard garden.<br>Many of us have felt the effects of being in different built environments. Yet what this means for our health and wellbeing hasn’t received enough research attention. How do the offices, houses, hospitals, schools, neighbourhoods and spaces that we occupy day to day affect our health? Traditionally, our understanding of how architectural design affects the human body has centred around the transmission of communicable diseases, such as viruses. For instance, the postwar urban redesign of the UK’s tenements worked to address overcrowded, damp and poorly ventilated housing conditions that are associated with increased rates of infectious diseases such as tuberculosis. However, the health effects of the built environment may be significantly more far-reaching than this.<br>Enter the emerging field of&nbsp;neuroarchitecture&nbsp;– an interdisciplinary domain that explores how the built environment affects human brain function, behaviour, cognition and psychology. Initial research indicates that, beyond its influence on infectious diseases, architectural design and form might also actively contribute to increased levels of stress in the body, which in turn could increase the risk of so-called noncommunicable diseases (often referred to as ‘lifestyle diseases’), including neurodegenerative and psychiatric conditions such as Alzheimer’s, Parkinson’s disease, depression and anxiety.<br>A better understanding of how the built environment impacts our health in these ways could revolutionise building design and urban planning. Imagine being able to design spaces that not only don’t cause harm, but actually promote overall wellbeing. In many ways, this burgeoning field validates what many of us have long intuitively felt: architecture is not merely the backdrop to our lives, but a crucial determinant of how we live and thrive.<br>Rapid urbanisation lends an urgency to this research.&nbsp;The United Nations&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.un.org/development/desa/en/news/population/2018-revision-of-world-urbanization-prospects.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.un.org/development/desa/en/news/population/2018-revision-of-world-urbanization-prospects.html" target="_blank">estimates</a>that, by 2050, two-thirds of the global population will live in cities. In developed countries, people already spend most of their time indoors. Some vulnerable groups in Europe, such as the elderly, infants, young children and people with weakened immune systems, spend almost all of their time indoors. These numbers are likely to&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160412015300507" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0160412015300507" target="_blank">grow</a>&nbsp;due to the extreme and increasingly unpredictable weather patterns caused by climate change.<br>Meanwhile,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/20/9/5637" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/20/9/5637" target="_blank">studies</a>&nbsp;in neuroarchitecture reveal the impact of even small changes in architectural and urban design. For example, rooms with lower ceilings and smaller windows can increase stress&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272494422000470?via%3Dihub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272494422000470?via%3Dihub" target="_blank">responses</a>&nbsp;in the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/human-neuroscience/articles/10.3389/fnhum.2017.00477/full" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/human-neuroscience/articles/10.3389/fnhum.2017.00477/full" target="_blank">body</a>. Yes, that converted loft apartment with high ceilings, large windows, lots of natural light and timber floors in the real estate magazine might actually be a home environment that could help reduce your bodily stress.<br>Similarly, some high-contrast visual patterns in architecture, such as striped facades, acoustic panels and patterned carpets can cause visual&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://visualstress.info/2016-238.pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://visualstress.info/2016-238.pdf" target="_blank">discomfort</a>, and in extreme instances can&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://arrow.tudublin.ie/sdar/vol6/iss1/5/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://arrow.tudublin.ie/sdar/vol6/iss1/5/" target="_blank">lead</a>&nbsp;to migraines and seizures in vulnerable individuals. For instance, many hotels and cinemas use carpets with complex, high-contrast patterns in their hallways and lobbies to hide stains and wear and, in the case of facilities such as casinos, in a deliberate attempt to cause disorientation and impair decision-making processes. Additionally, the use of slatwall<a data-footref="1" href="about:blank#fn-1-4fa04a5359ad35b0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a>  has become increasingly common in contemporary architecture. Once you notice this slatted wall panelling, you see it everywhere. Yet these structures, often arranged in repetitive, high-contrast patterns, can be visually overwhelming.<br>At the other end of the spectrum, visually monotonous environments can have a negative effect on people. Such spaces are characterised by minimal variation in the placement of windows and doors, and a lack of distinguishing features or details – a highly minimalist or functional aesthetic that is prevalent in some contemporary architecture. For example, think about the interchangeable architectural landscapes found in many commercial districts across the United States and Canada. In many instances, it is difficult to tell one city from the next. This is particularly the case in newbuild tract housing<a data-footref="1" href="about:blank#fn-1-4fa04a5359ad35b0" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1-1]</a> neighbourhoods, or shopping malls and retail centres. These environments tend to elevate stress levels because they fail to engage our senses. In contrast, settings with varied design elements and distinctive features, such as a streetscape with collections of smaller stores and restaurants, like Camden Passage in London, provide mental stimulation and a sense of interest, which can help reduce stress and promote wellbeing.<br>Understanding the full impact of long-term exposure&nbsp;to stress-inducing architectural designs on human health is a work in progress. New insights are emerging from neuroimmunology: the study of the interaction between the immune system and the nervous system. This shows that one particularly concerning consequence of chronic stress is inflammation of the brain. Neuroinflammation is implicated in several neurodegenerative and psychiatric disorders, including&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/neuroscience/articles/10.3389/fnins.2019.00384/full" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/neuroscience/articles/10.3389/fnins.2019.00384/full" target="_blank">depression</a>,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1552526016301856" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1552526016301856" target="_blank">Alzheimer’s</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychiatry/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1356975/full" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychiatry/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2024.1356975/full" target="_blank">schizophrenia</a>. What’s more, neuroinflammatory conditions&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4774049/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4774049/" target="_blank">appear</a>&nbsp;more prevalent in urban areas, potentially due to factors such as pollution, reduced social cohesion, and increased stress associated with urban living. However, the established links between architecture and stress, and between stress and neuroinflammation, raise an overlooked question:&nbsp;Could bad architecture also be contributing to the development of neurodegenerative and psychiatric disorders?<br>You might think that being in stressful architectural environments isn’t that big a deal. But bear in mind&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/18/8/4305" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/18/8/4305" target="_blank">research</a>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272494422000470?via%3Dihub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272494422000470?via%3Dihub" target="_blank">shown</a>&nbsp;that certain building features, such as room size, wall shapes and window layouts, can&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0031938414003242?via%3Dihub" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0031938414003242?via%3Dihub" target="_blank">cause</a>&nbsp;stress without us realising it. Moreover, we often spend&nbsp;a lot&nbsp;of time in places with spatial stressors – in offices, homes and schools – and this ongoing exposure could gradually affect our mental and neurophysiological health.<br>To explore this further, our team at the University of Cambridge is researching the impact of architecture on neuroinflammation. Most recently, we conducted a pilot&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-5309/14/5/1292" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-5309/14/5/1292" target="_blank">study</a>&nbsp;to examine how buildings with different architectural features affected markers of brain inflammation linked to stress. Specifically, we looked at something called biophilic design – the incorporation of natural elements into architecture, such as plants and natural light.<br>Participants looked at images of two different high-rise buildings for nine minutes each. The first building – depicted in photorealistic images – is a proposed development in Montreal, Canada that showcased a moderate degree of biophilia with its fractalised design patterns (these are patterns that repeat at different scales, as occurs in nature), organic building materials such as timber, a visually complex and interesting design, and vegetation incorporated on balconies and elsewhere. The second building, built in 2011 and located in The Hague in the Netherlands, was less biophilic because it lacked fractalised patterns, vegetation and organic building materials, though it was similar in terms of its height, colour and level of design detail.<br><img src="https://images.aeonmedia.co/images/16d0cd87-d4d7-4ebf-900a-c345d2646702/insert-2-farmhouse_precht_006-1.jpg?width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><img src="https://images.aeonmedia.co/images/0bf33162-f10e-40be-b228-a52cb0f64f91/insert-1-farmhouse_precht_010.jpg?width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br><img src="https://images.aeonmedia.co/images/1c320b10-0b5b-453c-8c70-cb4e59e6d8db/insert-kroon-facade-02.jpg?width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>De Kroon Office and Residential Buildings exterior. Courtesy&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.rappenrapp.com/project/de-kroon/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.rappenrapp.com/project/de-kroon/" target="_blank">Rapp+Rapp</a>/Photo by Kim Zwarts<br><img src="https://images.aeonmedia.co/images/370b95a1-9416-448e-a135-d49692b1d5b6/insert-kroon-interior-jpg.jpg?width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>De Kroon Office and Residential Buildings interior. Courtesy&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.rappenrapp.com/project/de-kroon/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.rappenrapp.com/project/de-kroon/" target="_blank">Rapp+Rapp</a>/Photo by Kim Zwarts<br>At the same time as the participants looked at these two building types, we measured their electrical brain activity using electroencephalography (EEG), a non-invasive method that involves wearing a head cap with electrodes. We used an innovative technique to infer signs of acute brain inflammation by comparing our participants’ brain activity with historical data showing associations between blood markers of inflammation and EEG recordings.<br>We found that participants exhibited lower levels of brain inflammation when exposed to the building with higher biophilia. This provides tentative evidence that integrating more biophilic or natural elements into architectural designs may help reduce brain inflammation, and expands on our current understanding of their stress-reducing benefits. This makes sense from an evolutionary perspective: humans evolved in natural environments, so we are&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.routledge.com/Cognitive-Architecture-Designing-for-How-We-Respond-to-the-Built-Environment/Sussman-Hollander/p/book/9780367468590" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.routledge.com/Cognitive-Architecture-Designing-for-How-We-Respond-to-the-Built-Environment/Sussman-Hollander/p/book/9780367468590" target="_blank">drawn</a>&nbsp;to the kind of natural environments in which our ancestors lived and we are healthier and less stressed in them. If further research supports our findings, it suggests that increasing natural light, integrating green spaces and designing spaces that encourage social interaction may help mitigate the negative impacts of urban living on neurological health.<br>What might this mean for everyday spaces? Consider schools – while it’s easy to recognise tangible risks such as overcrowding, dampness, poorly ventilated classrooms or hazardous materials such as asbestos, we often overlook the less visible impacts on neurophysiological health. For instance, how does visual stress from poor natural lighting and fluorescent light flicker affect students, especially those with neurodivergence or ADHD? What might be the long-term effects of low-ceilinged classrooms that lack natural light and other biophilic features? These are crucial questions that remain unanswered but are essential to ensure the health, wellbeing and best long-term learning outcomes for our children. Similar concerns apply to hospitals, workplaces and numerous other spaces.<br>The emerging research linking architectural design to neurological wellbeing marks a pivotal shift in our understanding of public health. We design our world and, in turn, it shapes us. The built environments we interact with daily are not passive elements but active factors that can inhibit or – with thoughtful consideration – enhance our neurological state and holistic wellbeing. |<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://psyche.co/ideas/how-the-buildings-you-occupy-might-be-affecting-your-brain" target="_blank">https://psyche.co/ideas/how-the-buildings-you-occupy-might-be-affecting-your-brain</a> (21 November 2024)<br><br><br>For the highlighted words in the text, choose the correct synonym of definition:<br>
<br>burgeoning<br>
a) stagnating<br>
b) vanishing<br>
c) growing rapidly<br>
d) decreasing
<br>far-reaching<br>
a) having a broad impact<br>
b) wide-going<br>
c) local<br>
d) coming from abroad
<br>lend an urgency<br>
a) create a sense of immediacy<br>
b) stir up the situation<br>
c) decrease the importance<br>
d) Make it less relevant
<br>vulnerable groups<br>
a) at-risk populations<br>
b) wealthy individuals<br>
c) powerful organizations<br>
d) government agencies
<br>impair decision-making processes<br>
a) facilitate discussions<br>
b) encourage indecision<br>
c) improve clarity<br>
d) hinder the ability to make choices
<br>visually monotonous<br>
a) intricately designed<br>
b) dynamically appealing<br>
c) colorful<br>
d) lacking visual variety
<br>interchangeable architectural landscapes<br>
a) cultural heritage sites<br>
b) similar building environments<br>
c) unique structures<br>
d) indigenous designs
<br>elevate stress levels<br>
a) develop calm<br>
b) induce pressure<br>
c) increase anxiety<br>
d) enhance relaxation
<br>distinctive features<br>
a) generic traits<br>
b) common elements<br>
c) ordinary aspects<br>
d) unique characteristics
<br>spatial stressors<br>
a) relaxing spaces<br>
b) environmental factors causing stress<br>
c) outdoor features<br>
d) recreational areas
<br>ongoing exposure<br>
a) sporadic appearance<br>
b) continuous contact<br>
c) infrequent interaction<br>
d) temporary presence
<br>tentative evidence<br>
a) solid facts<br>
b) preliminary proof<br>
c) conclusive findings<br>
d) strong assertions
<br>biophilic<br>
a) hostile to living things<br>
b) design approach connecting humans with nature<br>
c) technologically innovative<br>
d) exclamation, contraction of “by our Philip”
<br>mitigate<br>
a) worsen<br>
b) ignore<br>
c) intensify<br>
d) reduce the severity
<br>pivotal shift<br>
a) constant state<br>
b) significant change<br>
c) minor adjustment<br>
d) unrelated transformation
<br>
<br>
<br>Look up this word<a href="about:blank#fnref-1-4fa04a5359ad35b0" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a><a href="about:blank#fnref-1-1-4fa04a5359ad35b0" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/how-the-buildings-you-occupy-might-be-affecting-your-brain.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/How the buildings you occupy might be affecting your brain.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 10:12:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.aeonmedia.co/images/3ecb8e58-5348-4eb5-a791-cf87164f250c/rt-nest-perkins-and-will.jpg?top=4&amp;left=0&amp;cropWidth=1936&amp;cropHeight=1089&amp;width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto" length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.aeonmedia.co/images/3ecb8e58-5348-4eb5-a791-cf87164f250c/rt-nest-perkins-and-will.jpg?top=4&amp;left=0&amp;cropWidth=1936&amp;cropHeight=1089&amp;width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Is standing at your desk actually better than sitting? Here’s what the evidence says]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/profiles/josephine-chau-154603" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/josephine-chau-154603" target="_blank">Josephine Chau </a>Published: September 11, 2023 10.08pm CEST<br>In modern life, many of us spend the majority of our waking hours sitting. A <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://journals.physiology.org/doi/abs/10.1152/physrev.00022.2022" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://journals.physiology.org/doi/abs/10.1152/physrev.00022.2022" target="_blank">recent review</a> of the research has reiterated the harmful health impacts of prolonged, unbroken periods of sitting. <br>Many workplaces have adopted sit-stand desks, which allow you to sit down or stand up with the push of a button or lever, to reduce the harms of prolonged sitting.<br>But how much better is standing? And are there risks of too much standing? Here’s what the research says about the risks of too much sitting and standing, and whether it’s worth investing in – or ditching – a sit-stand desk. <br><br>Read more: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/covid-saw-us-sitting-longer-and-diabetes-rose-globally-by-16-in-2-years-time-to-get-moving-171945" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/covid-saw-us-sitting-longer-and-diabetes-rose-globally-by-16-in-2-years-time-to-get-moving-171945" target="_blank">COVID saw us sitting longer – and diabetes rose globally by 16% in 2 years. Time to get moving</a><br><br><br>People who sit a lot have <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://journals.lww.com/acsm-msse/fulltext/2019/06000/sedentary_behavior_and_health__update_from_the.18.aspx" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://journals.lww.com/acsm-msse/fulltext/2019/06000/sedentary_behavior_and_health__update_from_the.18.aspx" target="_blank">higher chances of developing chronic diseases</a> such as type 2 diabetes, heart disease, and some cancers, and having a shorter lifespan. Prolonged sitting can also lead to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.3389/fspor.2021.760533" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fspor.2021.760533" target="_blank">musculoskeletal complaints</a>, particularly in the neck and back.<br>Excessive sitting is even more harmful to health <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://journals.lww.com/acsm-msse/fulltext/2019/06000/sedentary_behavior_and_health__update_from_the.18.aspx" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://journals.lww.com/acsm-msse/fulltext/2019/06000/sedentary_behavior_and_health__update_from_the.18.aspx" target="_blank">among people who do very little exercise or who do not meet</a> the recommended levels of physical activity. <br>Being physically active is <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2017-098963" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1136/bjsports-2017-098963" target="_blank">important</a> for reducing the health risks linked to being sedentary, but it may not fully cancel out the negative effects of spending long hours sitting each day. <br><img alt="Young office workers sit around a large desk" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/547402/original/file-20230911-20-p2o2yl.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Excessive sitting is more harmful for those who do little exercise. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://unsplash.com/photos/HXOllTSwrpM" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://unsplash.com/photos/HXOllTSwrpM" target="_blank">Ant Rozetsky/Unsplash</a><br><br>Extended periods of standing can be harmful to musculoskeletal health. Prolonged standing may lead to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.1002/rnj.166" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.1002/rnj.166" target="_blank">musculoskeletal symptoms</a> such as muscle fatigue, leg swelling, varicose veins, and pain and discomfort in the low back and lower extremities (hips, knees, ankles and feet). <br>Recent research suggests <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gaitpost.2017.08.024" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gaitpost.2017.08.024" target="_blank">limiting standing to about 40 minutes</a> at a time, without a break, would reduce the chances of developing muscle and joint aches and pains due to prolonged standing. This applies to people who may or may not have had symptoms before. <br>Not everyone who stands for prolonged periods will experience these musculoskeletal symptoms, and some people may be more resilient to the effects of prolonged standing than others. <br>However, even if you take a break from standing, if you have previously developed standing-related aches and pains, you’re more likely to experience them again when you <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.1080/00140139.2014.893027" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00140139.2014.893027" target="_blank">resume standing</a>. <br><br>Read more: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/how-the-media-oversold-standing-desks-as-a-fix-for-inactivity-at-work-83808" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/how-the-media-oversold-standing-desks-as-a-fix-for-inactivity-at-work-83808" target="_blank">How the media oversold standing desks as a fix for inactivity at work</a><br><br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://journals.physiology.org/doi/abs/10.1152/physrev.00022.2022" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://journals.physiology.org/doi/abs/10.1152/physrev.00022.2022" target="_blank">Reducing or interrupting sitting</a> by standing up or moving around can improve your blood circulation, metabolism, heart health, mental health and lifespan. <br>Modelling studies show that <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34201369/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34201369/" target="_blank">swapping one hour of sitting each day for one hour of standing</a> leads to improvements in waist circumference, fat and cholesterol levels.<br>The benefit is even greater when sitting is replaced with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://ijbnpa.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12966-015-0280-7" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://ijbnpa.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12966-015-0280-7" target="_blank">walking or moderate-to-vigorous activity</a>. <br>Interrupting prolonged sitting time with as little as <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.2337/dc11-1931" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.2337/dc11-1931" target="_blank">two minutes of walking every 20 minutes</a> or <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://journals.lww.com/acsm-msse/abstract/2023/05000/breaking_up_prolonged_sitting_to_improve.9.aspx" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://journals.lww.com/acsm-msse/abstract/2023/05000/breaking_up_prolonged_sitting_to_improve.9.aspx" target="_blank">five minutes of walking every 30 minutes</a> can improve blood glucose, fat, and cholesterol levels. <br>Other research shows breaking up prolonged sitting time with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.2337/dc15-2336" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.2337/dc15-2336" target="_blank">three minutes of light walking or simple resistance exercises</a>, such as squats and calf raises, every 30 minutes is also effective. <br><br>Sit-stand desks can effectively <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apergo.2019.01.015" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apergo.2019.01.015" target="_blank">reduce sitting time during the workday</a> among desk-based workers. Sit-stand desk users tend to alternate between sitting and standing postures, instead of standing up for extended periods. <br>However, the extent of developing a new habit of working while standing up varies, and many users revert to their previous way of working sitting down in the longer term. <br>Sit-stand desks alone are not sufficient to reduce desk-based workers’ sitting time. Employers and organisations must <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph16030516" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph16030516" target="_blank">factor this into their workplace policies, environment and culture</a> to ensure “sit less and move more” initiatives are effectively delivered and sustained.<br><br>If you already have a sit-stand desk, whether you should keep or get rid of it will depend on a range of factors.<br>Think about your usage patterns. Do you use your desk regularly in a standing position, or do you mainly use it sitting down? <br>Consider your comfort. Does standing or sitting for prolonged periods while working lead to any discomfort or fatigue in your body? If so, you may need to adjust your sit-stand routine or include extra supports, such as a floor mat for more comfortable standing or a foot rest for safer sitting, to avoid injury. <br><br>Read more: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/get-a-proper-chair-dont-eat-at-your-desk-and-no-phones-in-the-loo-how-to-keep-your-home-workspace-safe-and-hygienic-143535" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/get-a-proper-chair-dont-eat-at-your-desk-and-no-phones-in-the-loo-how-to-keep-your-home-workspace-safe-and-hygienic-143535" target="_blank">Get a proper chair, don't eat at your desk, and no phones in the loo – how to keep your home workspace safe and hygienic</a><br><br>Assess your desk ergonomics. Is your <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.worksafe.qld.gov.au/safety-and-prevention/hazards/hazardous-manual-tasks/working-with-computers/setting-up-your-workstation" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.worksafe.qld.gov.au/safety-and-prevention/hazards/hazardous-manual-tasks/working-with-computers/setting-up-your-workstation" target="_blank">sit-stand desk set up</a> ergonomically safe for working in both sitting and standing positions? Proper ergonomics are essential to ensure you work in a safe and comfortable way [in the office and from home](<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.safeworkaustralia.gov.au/sites/default/files/2020-05/Working_from_home_Workstation_Setup" target="_blank">https://www.safeworkaustralia.gov.au/sites/default/files/2020-05/Working_from_home_Workstation_Setup</a>_ Guide-COVID-19.pdf). <br><img alt="img" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/547434/original/file-20230911-23-vlazi6.png?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Here’s what ergonomically safe positions look like for sitting and standing. [Safe Work Australia](<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.safeworkaustralia.gov.au/sites/default/files/2020-05/Working_from_home_Workstation_Setup" target="_blank">https://www.safeworkaustralia.gov.au/sites/default/files/2020-05/Working_from_home_Workstation_Setup</a>_ Guide-COVID-19.pdf), <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" target="_blank">CC BY</a><br>Reflect on your health needs. Will reducing and breaking up prolonged sitting time with standing alleviate discomfort due to sitting or contribute to improving your metabolic and heart health? Standing up and moving around regularly throughout the workday will achieve similar benefits regardless of your desk type. <br>If you have an existing health condition or ongoing musculoskeletal symptoms, seek advice from a health care professional or ask your employer about organising an assessment with an ergonomics specialist. Expert guidance can help you make an informed decision about your sit-stand desk. <br>Finally, weigh up the cost and space requirements of your sit-stand desk. If you are not using it in a standing position much, maybe it’s just taking up space and not providing a return on your investment? <br>Ultimately, the decision to keep or ditch your sit-stand desk will come down to a balance of these considerations. <br><img alt="Woman stands at desk" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/547403/original/file-20230911-21-7aq7zl.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>You’ll need to balance a number of considerations to determine if standing at work is worth it. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/side-view-african-american-female-graphic-1433983007" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/side-view-african-american-female-graphic-1433983007" target="_blank">Shutterstock</a><br><br>Physical activity guidelines from governments and health-related agencies, such as those from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.health.gov.au/topics/physical-activity-and-exercise/physical-activity-and-exercise-guidelines-for-all-australians/for-adults-18-to-64-years" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.health.gov.au/topics/physical-activity-and-exercise/physical-activity-and-exercise-guidelines-for-all-australians/for-adults-18-to-64-years" target="_blank">Australia</a> and the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/physical-activity" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/physical-activity" target="_blank">World Health Organization</a>, recommend adults limit the amount of time spent sitting. Interrupting and replacing sitting time with physical activity of any intensity – even light intensity – has health benefits. <br>The WHO further recommends adults “aim to do more than the recommended levels of moderate- to vigorous-intensity physical activity” to reduce the harmful health effects of high levels of sitting. <br>In other words, just standing is not enough to reduce the harms of prolonged sitting. We need to sit less and move more. <br><br>Read more: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/research-check-will-binge-watching-tv-increase-your-risk-for-alzheimers-disease-and-diabetes-84264" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/research-check-will-binge-watching-tv-increase-your-risk-for-alzheimers-disease-and-diabetes-84264" target="_blank">Research Check: will binge-watching TV increase your risk for Alzheimer's disease and diabetes?</a><br>]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/is-standing-at-your-desk-actually-better-than-sitting.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/Is standing at your desk actually better than sitting.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 12:08:43 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/547402/original/file-20230911-20-p2o2yl.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/547402/original/file-20230911-20-p2o2yl.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lost in translation: five common English phrases you may be using incorrectly]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 A few of those sayings that most people tend to get wrong.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/lost-in-translation-five-common-english-phrases-you-may-be-using-incorrectly.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/Lost in translation five common English phrases you may be using incorrectly.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[[[Simon Horobin]]]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 17:25:07 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/141776/original/image-20161014-30262-i4l8sr.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/141776/original/image-20161014-30262-i4l8sr.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Polluted Lakes Are Being Cleansed Using Floating Wetlands Made of Trash]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:PerpetualPlanet" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#PerpetualPlanet</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:PlanetPioneers" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#PlanetPioneers</a> 
 <br><br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.wired.com/author/hannah-rose-richter/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.wired.com/author/hannah-rose-richter/" target="_blank">Hannah Richter</a> Jul 25, 2024 7:00 AM<br><img alt="Image may contain Outdoors Flower Plant Nature Pond and Water" src="https://media.wired.com/photos/669921db6df451ee7586759b/master/w_2560%2Cc_limit/Prototype%2520_Bangladesh.%2520latest%2520pic%2520(1).jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Photograph: Abir Mahmud/University of Dhaka<br>On the banks of Nagdaha, a polluted and lotus-infested lake in Nepal, Soni Pradhanang is putting trash back into the water—on purpose.<br>She carefully assembles a platform of styrofoam and bamboo mats, then weaves it together with zip ties and coconut fiber, refuse from nearby tech stores. Then, she pokes 55 plants lush with red flowers through 2-inch holes in the platform, each plant set 6 inches apart. Though Pradhanang’s creation isn’t high-tech, it is effective, and one of the most affordable water-filtration systems available. “I’m cheap,” she says, laughing.<br>Pradhanang, a hydrologist at the University of Rhode Island who studies water-quality monitoring and modeling, has spent the past seven years working on her trash-based contraptions. Called floating treatment wetland systems (FTWS), these are 4-foot by 6-foot buoyant platforms topped with plants. When their roots are submerged in contaminated water, the plants suck pollutants into their stems and leaves as they grow. In turn, they leave behind dissolved oxygen captured during photosynthesis, which supports life beneath the surface.<br>The hope with these devices is two-fold: that they will cleanse waters and recycle rubbish in parts of the world where budgets for either are incredibly tight.<br>Pradhanang is also the chief scientific technical adviser to The Small Earth Nepal, a Kathmandu Valley–based research and community engagement group. It has spent around five years building, testing, and implementing the first known trash-based wetland water-cleaning systems here in Nagdaha’s polluted waters, which contain high concentrations of nitrates and phosphates due to agricultural and urban runoff. Pradhananag and The Small Earth Nepal also operate sites with collaborators in Ajmer, India, and Dhaka, Bangladesh.<br><img alt="Image may contain Lake Nature Outdoors Water Aerial View Architecture and Building" src="https://media.wired.com/photos/6699222b827fa29235c61841/master/w_1600%2Cc_limit/Nagdaha%2520full%2520view_%2520Samyak%2520Prajapati%2520(1).JPG" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Groups of platforms installed in Nagdaha lake in Nepal. Photograph: Samyak Prajapati/The Small Earth Nepal<br>These floating treatment systems aren’t huge—each mat is around the dimensions of a full-size mattress—but they can connect to form clusters that treat larger areas of water. In Nagdaha, where FTWS have been bobbing lazily for nearly two years, there are five clusters, each with eight platforms. Results from The Small Earth Nepal show that the systems significantly reduce concentrations of nitrates, heavy metals, and phosphorus in the lake.<br>Pradhanang has always looked to South Asia for her water-quality projects. Born and raised in Kathmandu, Nepal, she intimately understands the water challenges Nepalese citizens face, including pollution in lakes and rivers from sewage, industry, and agriculture, limited water treatment facilities, and the need to use the same water body for multiple purposes, like washing clothes and bathing. Before the floating wetland project, Pradhanang worked with local farmers and foresters in Nepal to address their water needs in the face of climate change.<br>“My roots are back there,” says Pradhanang. “I am sort of automatically drawn towards the community that I have been a part of.”<br>In the US, floating treatment wetland systems have been steadily increasing over the past few years, driven both by companies scaling up production of proprietary, non-trash-based platforms, and cities taking note of others’ successes. Urban waterways like Baltimore’s Inner Harbor, Boston’s Charles River, and the Chicago River have all successfully deployed FTWS to clean their waters.<br>When Pradhanang wanted to try the systems on polluted water bodies in Nepal, she saw a barrier: They’re too expensive. The proprietary bases, which are usually made from recycled and water-resistant materials, cost upwards of $600 each in 2018. “That's gonna be, what, 70,000 Nepalese rupees apiece? That’s somebody’s one-year salary,” she says.<br>Instead, Pradhanang developed a method she calls “trash for cash,” where the “cash” is improved water quality. If you build the mats using local waste, she reasoned, they become nearly free. She first tested the idea in her Rhode Island lab in 2017, with materials like oyster traps, bubble wrap, and BPA-free plastic water bottles, to see if trash-based mats loaded with plants could improve water quality.<br><img alt="Image may contain Plant Potted Plant Water Waterfront Boat Transportation Vehicle Outdoors and Food" src="https://media.wired.com/photos/66992268f50831321187199c/master/w_1600%2Cc_limit/Floating_Mat_1%2520(1).jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>A floating treatment wetland system loaded with plants. Photograph: Samyak Prajapati/The Small Earth Nepal<br>Building your own FTWS is “a lot harder than you think,” says Sarah White, a water quality and treatment scientist at Clemson University in South Carolina. “There are not a lot of buoyant materials that remain watertight over time.”<br>When Pradhanang found a trash mix that could be fashioned into a platform and resist breaking down with age, she began talking to her colleagues in Nepal. By 2021, they had secured $78,000 in funding from the Asia-Pacific Network for Global Change Research, a research and policy funder, to operate a study across Nepal, India, and Bangladesh.<br>While Nagdaha and the Indian and Bangladeshi sites do not provide residents with drinking water, they do have cultural and religious significance. On her many visits to Nepal, Pradhanang has seen children swimming in Nagdaha’s murky water, dogs lapping at the shore, and women sitting on the banks to wash dishes and clothing. Pradhanang and The Small Earth Nepal wanted to beautify the lake as they cleaned it. They chose flowering plants that served both purposes: Indian shot (Canna indica) and scarlet sage (Salvia splendens), whose bright red flowers stand out against the gray water.<br>After installing the floating platforms in the fall of 2022, the researchers tested the water monthly and found results consistent with their <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://smallearthnepal.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/ftws_policy-brief.pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://smallearthnepal.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/ftws_policy-brief.pdf" target="_blank">lab trials</a>, which showed a 99 percent reduction in nitrate levels, 80 percent reduction in phosphates, 56 percent reduction in iron, and 55 percent reduction in ammonia. Dissolved oxygen concentrations increased by half. Their results have been submitted to the Journal of Civil Engineering for review.<br>Growing flowering plants can add aesthetic value to a body of water, but the collaboration is staying away from growing food on the platforms, since the plants build up such high concentrations of pollutants. But people aren’t the only ones intrigued by the floating wetlands; geese and ducks flock to the mats, sitting on the platforms and pooping phosphorus-rich excrement into the water.<br>Pradhanang came up with a clever solution for the mischievous mallards: She tied silver ribbons around the stems of the plants, whose sharp glare drove away the birds. Though the scientists don’t want geese on the FTWS, pollinators like bees and small birds are more than welcome—as are the diverse microbial life-forms that exist on the plant roots and digest pollutants in the water for energy.<br>“There’s a real kind of, ‘If you build it, they will come’ phenomenon that’s associated with the floating wetlands,” says Max Rome, who did his PhD on FTWS in Boston’s Charles River and now works at the Charles River Watershed Association. “These systems are really effective for creating wetland biodiversity in a place where there’s just not room for wetlands.”<br>Though the trash-based systems solve some water-pollution problems, they leave others—namely, microplastics. Incorporating local trash into the mats shouldn’t make things worse overall—much of the trash is gathered from the water in the first place—but high plastic content in the water means that it can remain a risk to locals’ health, even after cleansing.<br>While Pradhanang and outside researchers have flagged concerns about incorporating styrofoam and other plastics into the trash-based FTWS, they say that the benefits of the mats generally outweigh the costs. “If you can use a waste product that would then just be normally in the water,” says White, “and you can use it to make a product that is actually helping to clean the water, it’s amazing.”<br>However, Pradhanang emphasizes that the floating treatment systems are only providing a net good if they are maintained properly; if people don’t take care of them, there’s the risk their components become unfastened and turn back into trash.<br>Community responses to the floating treatment wetland systems have largely been positive. But to give them staying power once the researchers leave, “we have to demonstrate the effectiveness of these systems,” explains Dr. Ritu Singh, an assistant professor at the Central University of Rajasthan and the FTWS collaboration’s lead for India. If residents don’t know the mats’ water-cleaning properties, the systems become “just a burden for locals to take care of,” she adds.<br>That’s not a problem specific to the tri-nation collaboration. White spoke of homeowners in the US South who didn’t know floating mats near their homes provided water treatment benefits, and a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-031-18412-3_8" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-031-18412-3_8" target="_blank">study on Sri Lankan floating wetlands</a> found that locals often thought the systems were simply aesthetic.<br>Once locals are educated about the FTWS, their maintenance is pretty minimal—biannual prunings and root trimmings suffice. But with the grant money from the Asia-Pacific Network for Global Change Research all spent, Pradhanang and The Small Earth Nepal are in the process of transitioning the floating wetlands’ maintenance to local groups.<br>Throughout the past year, the collaboration has run workshops on the systems’ benefits and care instructions, as well as a policy briefing to the mayors, water chairmen, and community groups at all three sites. They are also offering advertising space on the sides of the platforms to incentivize people to take ownership of the systems and use the money generated to maintain them.<br>To expand beyond the three research sites—let alone maintain the ones that exist—the researchers emphasize the need for local policy and funding. While the FTWS are low-cost, money is still needed to cover people’s time and labor, as well as the bamboo mats and plants used in the platforms.<br>The Small Earth Nepal reported that the Kathmandu Valley Water Supply Board has shown interest in implementing the FTWS at other sites, and Pradhanang is traveling to Nepal this month to discuss next steps. She has also shared the methods of her trash-based FTWS experiments with a university in Banjarmasin, Indonesia, which is hoping to try these systems on its own polluted waters.<br>Though funding and scale are always in the back of her mind, Pradhanang has found that communicating with local residents about their needs and opinions is the most important step towards success with floating treatment wetland systems. “We talk about phosphorus, we talk about ammonia, we talk about nitrate—for a community, it means nothing,” she says. “For a community, they need clean water.”<br><br>The world needs protecting, now more than ever. But preserving the natural world and advancing human knowledge requires innovative and pioneering solutions. In this series, WIRED, in partnership with the Rolex Perpetual Planet Initiative, highlights the individuals and communities working to solve some of our most pressing environmental and scientific challenges. Through the Perpetual Planet Initiative, Rolex supports those who go above and beyond to safeguard and preserve our planet for the next generations. <a href=".?query=tag:PerpetualPlanet" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#PerpetualPlanet</a> <a href=".?query=tag:PlanetPioneers" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#PlanetPioneers</a><br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.wired.com/story/planet-pioneers-nagdaha-small-earth-nepal-soni-pradhanang-ftws-floating-treatment-wetland-systems-water-cleaning-pollution/" target="_blank">https://www.wired.com/story/planet-pioneers-nagdaha-small-earth-nepal-soni-pradhanang-ftws-floating-treatment-wetland-systems-water-cleaning-pollution/</a> (9 January 2025)<br><br>
<br>Explain how floating treatment wetland systems work.
<br>What reasons are there for using trash for the FTWS in Nepal?
<br>FTWS attracted wildlife to Nagdaha lake, which posed new problems. What were they, and how did Soni Pradhanang address them?
<br>What role do aesthetics play in the projects treating polluted water in general, and in Nagdaha lake, specifically?
<br>Explain the importance of the local residents for such a project to work.
<br><br>Where do you find the evidence in the text?<br>
<br>Soni Pradhanang's floating treatment wetland systems (FTWS) are primarily constructed using high-tech, expensive materials.
<br>The FTWS platforms in Nagdaha lake are approximately the size of a full-size mattress.
<br>Proprietary FTWS bases cost around $600 each in 2018, which is equivalent to a year's salary for some in Nepal.
<br>The trash-based FTWS have shown no significant reduction in nitrate levels in Nagdaha lake.
<br>Pradhanang's "trash for cash" method involves using local waste to construct FTWS platforms, making them nearly cost-free.
<br>The researchers chose plants like Indian shot and scarlet sage for their FTWS due to their ability to absorb pollutants and their aesthetic appeal.
<br>Growing food on the FTWS platforms is encouraged by the researchers as a way to utilize the cleaned water.
<br>The incorporation of styrofoam and other plastics in the trash-based FTWS is universally considered problematic by researchers.
<br>Maintenance of the FTWS requires daily attention and complex procedures.
<br>The Kathmandu Valley Water Supply Board has expressed interest in implementing FTWS at additional sites.
]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/polluted-lakes-are-being-cleansed-with-trash.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/Polluted Lakes Are Being Cleansed with Trash.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 07:45:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://media.wired.com/photos/669921db6df451ee7586759b/master/w_2560%2Cc_limit/Prototype%2520_Bangladesh.%2520latest%2520pic%2520(1).jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://media.wired.com/photos/669921db6df451ee7586759b/master/w_2560%2Cc_limit/Prototype%2520_Bangladesh.%2520latest%2520pic%2520(1).jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sitting on the floor vs sitting on a chair – which is better for you?]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/profiles/nachiappan-chockalingam-435477" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/nachiappan-chockalingam-435477" target="_blank">Nachiappan Chockalingam </a><br>Professor of Clinical Biomechanics, University of Staffordshire<br>Published: July 23, 2020 2.17pm CEST<br>For thousands of years, humans have rested on the ground using variations of a squat, cross-legged or a kneeling position. And despite the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/08/chairs-history-witold-rybczynski/497657/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/08/chairs-history-witold-rybczynski/497657/" target="_blank">availability of chairs and things to sit on</a>, sitting on the floor is still common [in many cultures](<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://medium.com/bigberry/korean-floor-culture-2f7b6849ca2d#:~:text=Next" target="_blank">https://medium.com/bigberry/korean-floor-culture-2f7b6849ca2d#:~:text=Next</a> to China%2C Japan and,TV%2C playing and even sleeping.). <br>According to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3291701/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3291701/" target="_blank">reports</a>, many English-speaking people refer to floor sitting as “Indian style”, though it’s also known as “Turkish style”. In Korea, it’s called “Yangban style” – named after the traditional ruling class. While in Japan, the formal way to sit is called seiza, which involves sitting on the heels with the knees resting on the floor. <br>In yoga, sitting cross-legged on the floor is known as sukhasana or lotus – claimed to have been designed to stretch the muscles, improve posture and bring peace of mind. Some people claim that if you sit in this position while eating it [helps digestion](<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://blog.decathlon.in/articles/learn-padmasana-and-its-benefits#:~:text=Doing" target="_blank">https://blog.decathlon.in/articles/learn-padmasana-and-its-benefits#:~:text=Doing</a> the lotus pose also,by kindling the digestive fire.&amp;text=This is one of the,stability of the pelvic muscles.). <br>These cross-legged, squatting and kneeling positions <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/International_Encyclopedia_of_Ergonomics.html?id=Ih-z6lkTO8EC&amp;redir_esc=y" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/International_Encyclopedia_of_Ergonomics.html?id=Ih-z6lkTO8EC&amp;redir_esc=y" target="_blank">stretch your hips, legs, pelvis and spine</a> helping to promote natural flexibility and movement. Given that people now spend <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2731178" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2731178" target="_blank">increasing amounts of time sitting</a> during the day, should we be opting for the floor over a chair in the interest of our health and wellbeing?<br><br>Anecdotal and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10803548.2016.1152736" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10803548.2016.1152736" target="_blank">clinical</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/art.24737" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/art.24737" target="_blank">evidence</a> shows that different ways of sitting place different physical stresses on our bodies. Sitting for a long time in the same position normally affects the structure of your low back, called the lumbar region of the spine and the movement characteristics of your pelvis. And it’s believed this might lead to health problems in the long run, such as arthritis. <br>This is why people are normally advised to make use of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/ten-tips-for-looking-after-your-back-while-youre-sitting-down-140650" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/ten-tips-for-looking-after-your-back-while-youre-sitting-down-140650" target="_blank">appropriate supports or assistive devices</a> and to switch positions often when sitting for a long time.<br><br>Read more: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/ten-tips-for-looking-after-your-back-while-youre-sitting-down-140650" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/ten-tips-for-looking-after-your-back-while-youre-sitting-down-140650" target="_blank">Ten tips for looking after your back while you're sitting down</a><br><br>Researchers and doctors <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1356689X12000938?casa_token=p8ZUV7nul-kAAAAA:ljoWQESnA5_zpEUIh3rZGjq9nXN083fnlkYRvym4kL0CoNOaLAEkc4n4UnxBymKGTJB9QAzacg" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1356689X12000938?casa_token=p8ZUV7nul-kAAAAA:ljoWQESnA5_zpEUIh3rZGjq9nXN083fnlkYRvym4kL0CoNOaLAEkc4n4UnxBymKGTJB9QAzacg" target="_blank">have looked</a> at the ergonomics of sitting on chairs and have provided a variety of tips on sitting upright and how to avoid long-term health problems. But there is actually little scientific evidence on sitting on the floor. <br><img alt="Little boy and girl sitting on the floor playing with toy train set." src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/348868/original/file-20200722-30-2ats7a.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"> <br>Children often naturally gravitate to the floor. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.pexels.com/photo/adorable-little-boy-and-girl-playing-with-toy-train-3771505/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.pexels.com/photo/adorable-little-boy-and-girl-playing-with-toy-train-3771505/" target="_blank">pexels</a><br>Despite this, health professionals are [increasingly](<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.uprightpose.com/blog/sitting-on-the-floor-posture-health-benefits/#:~:text=In" target="_blank">https://www.uprightpose.com/blog/sitting-on-the-floor-posture-health-benefits/#:~:text=In</a> fact%2C sitting on the,and conscious effort to develop.) advising that sitting on the floor helps to maintain the natural curvature of the spine and so helps people sit more upright and improve posture. It’s also claimed that sitting on the floor helps to improve strength and flexibility and can help you avoid lower-back pain. <br><br>Though there is limited research on floor sitting, there may be some truth to these claims. This is because the spinal structure shows an inward natural spine curvature at the lower back called lumbar lordosis. When sitting on the floor, the lumbar lordosis is relatively low, which is closer to our natural position and posture. <br>Sitting cross-legged could also bring about the natural and correct curvature both at the upper and lower back, effectively stabilising the lower back and pelvis region. But that said, certain <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4591449/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4591449/" target="_blank">sitting postures</a> rotate the pelvis backwards and the lumbar lordosis is more flattened than it is when sitting on a chair, which can cause problems. <br><br>Previous <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22396838/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22396838/" target="_blank">research</a> has shown that when sitting on the floor, the changes in the lumbar lordosis mostly occur at a vertebral or the segmental level at the lower end of the spine. In this respect, sitting on the floor can easily aggravate lower back pain. To avoid this, sitting with a lordotic lumbar curve is important.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://europepmc.org/article/med/20552952" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://europepmc.org/article/med/20552952" target="_blank">Studies</a> also claim sitting with your legs crossed on a chair induces a greater load on the intervertebral discs and spine – especially when in a slumped position as this can further increase disc pressure and aggravate chronic low back pain. This is why it’s very important to use the correct sitting posture. <br><img alt="Young Black man sitting cross-legged, meditating." src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/348867/original/file-20200722-20-52ocis.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>People often sit on the floor as part of a yoga or meditation practice. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/young-black-man-doing-yoga-sitting-1243651420" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/young-black-man-doing-yoga-sitting-1243651420" target="_blank">Evgeny Atamanenko/Shutterstock</a><br>The exact relationship between sitting posture, how and which muscles work and low back pain still needs to be established. But scientific <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://europepmc.org/article/med/20552952" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://europepmc.org/article/med/20552952" target="_blank">research</a> shows that some lumbo-pelvic muscles, the muscles in our hip regions, play an important role in postural stabilisation. <br>There is also some <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10803548.2016.1152736" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10803548.2016.1152736" target="_blank">evidence</a> that sitting on the floor with folded legs is less harmful when compared to other sitting postures, such as squatting and sitting on the floor with stretched legs. Indeed, one study found that squatting along with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/art.24737" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/art.24737" target="_blank">cycling</a> were both risk factors for knee osteoarthritis. <br>While high-quality scientific evidence is still lacking on the benefits of floor sitting, it is becoming a growing trend – particularly among people choosing to adopt more minimalist or <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/furniturefree/?hl=en" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.instagram.com/explore/tags/furniturefree/?hl=en" target="_blank">furniture-free lifestyles</a>.<br>So what’s the best way to sit? While a comfortable sitting position will probably vary from person to person, the key to good sitting is <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003687019301279" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003687019301279" target="_blank">regular movement and changing your position often</a>. These changes could be as simple as moving side to side in the chair or standing up and stretching every now and again. Basically, listen to your body, it will tell you what it needs.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/sitting-on-the-floor-vs-sitting-on-a-chair.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/Sitting on the floor vs sitting on a chair.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 12:13:08 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/348868/original/file-20200722-30-2ats7a.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/348868/original/file-20200722-30-2ats7a.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Standing Desks are Bad for your Health – New Study]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/profiles/jack-mcnamara-1352749" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/jack-mcnamara-1352749" target="_blank">Jack McNamara</a>&nbsp;Published: October 22, 2024 11.55am CEST<br>The global market for standing desks is booming, projected to reach&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.gminsights.com/industry-analysis/standing-desk-market" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.gminsights.com/industry-analysis/standing-desk-market" target="_blank">US$12.6 billion by 2032</a>&nbsp;(£9.7 billion). These desks have been hailed as a simple fix for the health risks associated with sitting all day. However, recent research suggests that standing might not be the health booster many hoped for.<br>A&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39412356/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/39412356/" target="_blank">new study</a>&nbsp;from Australia involving over 83,000 participants found that prolonged standing may not improve heart health and could even increase the risk of certain circulatory problems.&nbsp;<br>Researchers discovered that standing for extended periods did not reduce the risk of heart disease and stroke. In fact, spending too much time either sitting or standing was linked to a higher risk of problems such as varicose veins and feeling dizzy or lightheaded when you stand up.<br>The phrase “sitting is the new smoking” has&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=sitting+is+the+new+smoking&amp;year_start=1800&amp;year_end=2022&amp;corpus=en&amp;smoothing=3" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=sitting+is+the+new+smoking&amp;year_start=1800&amp;year_end=2022&amp;corpus=en&amp;smoothing=3" target="_blank">become popular</a>&nbsp;in the past decade, highlighting the dangers of a sedentary lifestyle. Prolonged sitting has been associated with&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30817262/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30817262/" target="_blank">obesity, diabetes and cardiovascular diseases</a>. In response, standing desks emerged as a trendy solution, offering a&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34558602/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34558602/" target="_blank">way to reduce sitting</a>&nbsp;time without drastically changing daily routines.<br>But was there solid evidence to support the benefits of standing desks?&nbsp;<br>Much of the enthusiasm was based on limited studies that didn’t comprehensively assess long-term health consequences. This gap in knowledge prompted researchers to investigate further.&nbsp;<br>In the new study, participants wore devices to track their sitting, standing and physical activity over several years. This objective measurement provided accurate data, reducing the inaccuracies&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32131845/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32131845/" target="_blank">often found in self-reported information</a>. The researchers found that sitting for more than ten hours a day was associated with a higher risk of heart disease and stroke.&nbsp;<br>However, simply standing more didn’t mitigate this risk. In fact, standing for extended periods was linked to an increased risk of circulatory problems.&nbsp;<br>Prolonged standing can cause blood to pool in the legs, leading to&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25047584/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25047584/" target="_blank">conditions such as varicose veins</a>.&nbsp;<br>The study’s large sample size and use of objective data strengthen the reliability of these findings. However, as an observational study, it cannot definitively establish cause and effect. Also, the average age of participants was around 61 years, which may limit how these results apply to younger people.<br><img alt="A man's lower legs covered in varicose veins." src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/626925/original/file-20241021-15-2y6k27.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Standing for long periods can increase the risk of varicose veins.&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/elderly-mans-bare-legs-varicose-veins-2509061249" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/elderly-mans-bare-legs-varicose-veins-2509061249" target="_blank">sutulastock/Shutterstock</a><br><br>These findings suggest that simply swapping sitting for standing isn’t a perfect solution. Our bodies respond better to regular movement rather than static positions, whether that’s sitting or standing.&nbsp;<br>Incorporating short walks, stretching or light exercises throughout the day can interrupt long periods of inactivity and offer&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33239350/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33239350/" target="_blank">significant health benefits</a>.<br>Workplace interventions promoting movement have shown promise. Researchers found that office workers who reduced their sitting time by adding periods of&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25113139/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25113139/" target="_blank">standing and light activity</a>&nbsp;saw improvements in blood sugar levels and other health markers.&nbsp;<br>Another study indicated that alternating between sitting and standing, combined with brief walks, was&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6334681/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6334681/" target="_blank">more effective for health</a>&nbsp;than standing alone.<br>Sit-stand desks, designed to facilitate easy position changes, offer a promising solution. They promote&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22374636/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22374636/" target="_blank">frequent posture changes</a>&nbsp;and can alleviate discomfort associated with prolonged static positions. Some models even feature reminders to encourage regular movement, integrating activity into the workday.<br>Getting more physical activity into our lives doesn’t have to be complex. Simple actions such as taking the stairs, walking to a colleague instead of emailing, or standing during phone calls can all contribute. Setting a timer to remind you to move every 30 minutes can help break up long periods of sitting or standing, empowering you to take control of your health.<br>Movement is key. Standing all day isn’t necessarily better than sitting – both have drawbacks when overdone. By focusing on regular physical activity and varying our positions, we can better address the health challenges posed by sedentary lifestyles. Small changes, such as taking short active breaks or incorporating stretching exercises, can make a&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33239350/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33239350/" target="_blank">significant difference</a>.<br>Ultimately, while standing desks offer an alternative to prolonged sitting, they shouldn’t be seen as a complete solution. Embracing a more active lifestyle, both in and out of the office, is likely to yield the greatest health benefits. It’s not just about standing or sitting; it’s about moving more and sitting less.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/standing-desks-are-bad-for-your-health-–-new-study.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/Standing Desks are Bad for your Health – New Study.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 15:11:26 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/626925/original/file-20241021-15-2y6k27.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/626925/original/file-20241021-15-2y6k27.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[‘Whatchamacallit’, ‘gizmo’ and ‘thingamajig’: what we say when we can’t find the right word – and why]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/profiles/ursula-kania-1540499" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/ursula-kania-1540499" target="_blank">Ursula Kania </a>Published: July 8, 2024 5.26pm CEST<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://bmcbiol.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12915-017-0405-3" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://bmcbiol.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12915-017-0405-3" target="_blank">Over 50,000 years ago</a>, humans started speaking and we’ve not shut up since. Sometimes, though, we struggle to remember the name of an object, a place, or a person we want to talk about. The technical term for this phenomenon is “lethologica”. <br>While severe word-finding difficulties can be due to serious neurological issues, such as a stroke or dementia, drawing the occasional, temporary blank is very common. Unsurprisingly, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13825585.2019.1641177" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13825585.2019.1641177" target="_blank">stress</a> doesn’t help, and it <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.00338/full" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/psychology/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.00338/full" target="_blank">gets worse as we age</a>.<br>But what can we do if we’re coming up empty yet still want to keep the conversation going?<br>Well, there are different ways of dealing with this problem. We can hesitate, using so-called fillers like “ehm” and “uh” to buy us some time, in the hope that the right word will make a delayed but triumphant appearance. <br>We can describe what we mean, hoping to still get the message across. (Recently, it took me a moment to figure out that the “flat things that look like doughnuts” my daughter was talking about were DVDs.) <br>We may even be able to recall certain formal characteristics of the word, like the first letter or sound, or how many syllables it has and generously offer these clues to the puzzled listener: “You know – this guy we met last week, I think his name starts with a G.”<br>This is why we also call this the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1991-14347-001" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1991-14347-001" target="_blank">tip-of-the-tongue phenomenon</a>. We’ve almost got it, and our brain is doing its best to use all stored bits of information (for example, on the word’s pronunciation and meaning) to come up with something useful to say, even if it isn’t the correct word itself.<br>Sometimes, this results in us making up words on the spot (referred to within linguistics as “spontaneous” or “ad-hoc coinages”). You may not find them in the dictionary, but they usually still make sense in context. <br>Even young children already come up with them in an attempt to put into useful practice what they’ve already learned about language – like the six-year-old referring to a women’s shampoo bottle as a “lady thing” in a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.museumofplay.org/app/uploads/2022/01/1-4-article-word-play.pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.museumofplay.org/app/uploads/2022/01/1-4-article-word-play.pdf" target="_blank">study</a> on language play. <br>My favourite example in this category, though, is a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://twitter.com/SophieRachael95/status/1115329983210242048" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://twitter.com/SophieRachael95/status/1115329983210242048" target="_blank">Tweet</a> about a German customer in a Welsh pub who couldn’t recall the word “cutlery” and politely asked for “food weapons”.<br>Last but certainly not least, we may use ready-made placeholders like “thingamajig”, “whatchamacallit” (for an object) or “what’s-his-name” (for a person).<br>Apparently, the struggle to find the right word is real and has been for some time, because the Oxford English Dictionary has its own category for these terms, labelled <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.oed.com/thesaurus/?classId=152065&amp;openAt=152068" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.oed.com/thesaurus/?classId=152065&amp;openAt=152068" target="_blank">“thing or person whose name is forgotten or unknown”</a>. It includes 64 entries and some records go back as far as the early middle English period (1100–1300).<br><img alt="img" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/604623/original/file-20240703-17-v5zj2f.png?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>The struggle to find a word is real and there are many documented words for things or people we have forgotten. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-vector/doubt-feeling-not-confident-concept-young-2026236602" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.shutterstock.com/image-vector/doubt-feeling-not-confident-concept-young-2026236602" target="_blank">Alphavector/Shutterstock</a><br>Not all of them are still used today. The last attested use for the strangely evocative “whiblin” was in 1652, for example, and “jiggumbob” is marked as obsolete.<br>Others, like “gizmo” or “doodah” are still going strong, though, and you can even buy “Whatchamacallits” and “Whozeewhatzits” – they are chocolate bars made by Hershey’s.<br>There are threads on Reddit dedicated to collecting placeholder words in <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskAnAmerican/comments/xax5en/how_do_you_call_things_in_english_you_dont_know/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AskAnAmerican/comments/xax5en/how_do_you_call_things_in_english_you_dont_know/" target="_blank">English</a> and from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.reddit.com/r/languagelearning/comments/f5zzj6/a_whatchamacallit_in_different_languages/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/languagelearning/comments/f5zzj6/a_whatchamacallit_in_different_languages/" target="_blank">around the world</a>. They are worth exploring, with gems like “doomaflitchie”, the Dutch “huppeldepup” and the German “dingsdabumsda”.<br>Next time you’re using “whatchamacallit”, appreciate it as your brain doing its best.<br>By the way: do you still remember the technical term for failing to recall the right word I introduced at the start of this article?<br>Yes? Congratulations!<br>No? Well, you and your brain know how to handle this.]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/whatchamacallit-gizmo-thingamajig.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/whatchamacallit gizmo thingamajig.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2024 14:49:16 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://images.theconversation.com/files/604623/original/file-20240703-17-v5zj2f.png?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/604623/original/file-20240703-17-v5zj2f.png?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why we are living in the age of the chair]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>9 November 2018 | Vybarr Cregan-Reid<br><img alt="Alamy Future historians may well look back on our modern age and see it as one defined by the ubiquity of chairs (Credit: Alamy)" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/1920xn/p06r2tsx.jpg.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>
Future historians may well look back on our modern age and see it as one defined by the ubiquity of chairs (Credit: Alamy)<br>Future historians looking back on the Anthropocene may see the defining technology of our modern period as the chair rather than the computer, and it is having a major impact on our bodies.<br>Why are there no chairs in the Bible, or in all 30,000 lines of Homer? Neither are there any in the play Hamlet – written in 1599. But by the middle of the 19th Century, it is a completely different story. In Charles Dickens’s Bleak House, suddenly there are 187 mentions of them. What changed?<br>With sitting sometimes being described as ‘the new smoking’, we know that spending too much time in chairs is bad for us. Not only are chairs unhealthy, but like air pollution, they are becoming almost impossible for modern humans to avoid.<br>When I started researching <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.octopusbooks.co.uk/books/detail.page?isbn=9781788401081" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.octopusbooks.co.uk/books/detail.page?isbn=9781788401081" target="_blank">my book</a> about how the world we have created around us is changing our bodies, I was surprised to discover just how rare chairs used to be. Now they’re everywhere – in offices, trains, cafés, restaurants, pubs, cars, concert halls, cinemas, doctor’s surgeries, hospitals, theatres, schools, lecture halls, and all over our houses (I guarantee you have more than you think).<br>If I was asked to make even a conservative estimate of the number of chairs in the world, I’d find it hard to go lower than eight to 10 per person. Applying that logic, there could be more than 60 billion of them on the planet. Surely chairs should be one of the universal signals that mark the arrival of our current geological epoch, the Anthropocene? Like other markers of our shift to a new time period, chairs are to be found on every continent.<br><img alt="Alamy This painting of Napoleon in the Chateaux of Versailles in 1809 shows the French emperor seated while all around remain standing (Credit: Alamy)" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/1920xn/p06r2sz8.jpg.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">This painting of Napoleon in the Chateaux of Versailles in 1809 shows the French emperor seated while all around remain standing (Credit: Alamy)<br>As to why there are suddenly so many chairs, there is no single clear reason. It is a confluence of fashion, politics, changing work habits, and the lust for comfort. The last of these requires no explanation in a culture where ease and comfort are among the strongest drivers of consumer decision-making.<br>While chairs began to appear with a little more frequency in the early modern period (1500-1800), it seems that they became much more popular during the Industrial Revolution.<br>Before the 18th Century, a chair was relatively easily come by, but the majority of the population had little use for them. Even today, it is not easy to sit on a hard wooden chair for sustained periods and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/sfurn/hd_sfurn.htm" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/sfurn/hd_sfurn.htm" target="_blank">upholstered</a> chairs were prohibitively expensive. But the fashion for a new reclining culture, which spread from the French court of the 18th Century, helped to popularise their early use.<br>For centuries before, chairs had persistently been associated with power, wealth and high status. They were about as widely used by the peasantry as a crown. There is an instructive stage direction in the First Folio of King Lear in which the monarch enters while being carried by servants “in a chair”. The idea of chairs as a symbol of status still persists today. The highest attainment in my own profession, academia, is called ‘a chair’. The individual that runs a meeting is called ‘a chair’. The head of a company is also a chairman or woman. And it is a truth, universally acknowledged, that the best chair in any office building always belongs to the boss.<br><img alt="Alamy Royal thrones typify the power that chairs have signified for much of human history (Credit: Alamy)" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/1920xn/p06r2sfz.jpg.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">Royal thrones typify the power that chairs have signified for much of human history (Credit: Alamy)<br>Once the use of chairs was democratised (particularly after the French Revolution in France and the 1832 Great Reform Acts in the UK), this coincided with a slow change in our working patterns. The majority of work done in the Victorian period would have been understood as manual labour or factory work.<br>But towards the end of the 19th Century, as the second wave of a technological revolution gathered pace with inventions such as the typewriter, telegraphy and the expanding uses of electricity, the labour market also began to change. The new category of office clerks was the fastest-growing occupational group in the latter half of the period. In 1851, the census suggests that fewer than <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://www.victorianweb.org/history/census.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://www.victorianweb.org/history/census.html" target="_blank">44,000 people</a> were performing administrative work. In just two decades, sedentary workers had more than doubled to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://www.victorianweb.org/history/census.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://www.victorianweb.org/history/census.html" target="_blank">91,000</a>.<br>Today, sedentary workers are in the majority. And, throughout the 20th Century, a forest of other sedentary activities have sprouted around us to match our new working lives.<br>Novel reading increased hugely in popularity throughout the 19th Century – and further sedentary leisure activities followed with the arrival of cinema, radio and television. More recently, computer gaming, media streaming and other screen-time activities lead us to sit still in contemplation. The Anthropocene human needs chairs to fulfil all of these ‘activities’.<br>If modern life presents us with a bouquet of sedentary behaviours, then chairs are the stalks. They are so necessary to leading a modern life that most of what we do seems unimaginable without them. Research conducted by the British Heart Foundation suggests that we enjoy about 9.5 hours per day of sedentary time. This means that modern humans are inactive for about 75% of their time. There are a few problems with this.<br>The health of our hard and soft tissues can be boiled down to the adage ‘use it or lose it’. Muscle and bone respond either to increased load or the cessation of use. Bones become denser or thinner while muscles get stronger or weaker. Seated so much, with most of the musculature in our backs disengaged as they recline in a chair, it is little wonder that with our weakened spines, back pain is now the number one cause of disability, globally.<br><img alt="Alamy Modern activities like video gaming, browsing the internet or watching television require us to remain seated (Credit: Alamy)" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/1920xn/p06r2tx6.jpg.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer"><br>Modern activities like video gaming, browsing the internet or watching television require us to remain seated (Credit: Alamy)<br>Just as we have an Anthropocene environment, we might equally class ourselves as Anthropocene humans. Palaeolithic humans died most frequently in infancy. Violence and injury were also common causes of mortality in later life. Modern humans, though, overwhelmingly die as a result of metabolic disorders such as type 2 diabetes, heart disease and some cancers – all strongly linked with inactivity: namely, chair use.<br>A 2012 study investigating the effects of inactivity collated behavioural data from 7,813 women and found that those that sat for ten hours a day had shorter telomeres (an indicator of cellular ageing). Their sedentary habits had aged them biologically by about eight years. Some studies even suggest that the effects of sitting for sustained periods cannot be offset by a little exercise.<br>These studies and many others attest to the fact that we should be thinking carefully about investing any further in our relatively new-found and passionate love affair with the chair.<br>This article <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/anthropocene-why-the-chair-should-be-the-symbol-for-our-sedentary-age-105319" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/anthropocene-why-the-chair-should-be-the-symbol-for-our-sedentary-age-105319" target="_blank"><strong></strong></a>*originally appeared* on The Conversation, and is republished under a Creative Commons licence. <br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20181108-the-anthropocene-should-be-known-as-the-age-of-the-chair" target="_blank">https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20181108-the-anthropocene-should-be-known-as-the-age-of-the-chair</a> (7 November 2024)]]></description><link>english/texts/gym4/why-we-are-living-in-the-age-of-the-chair.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/GYM4/Why we are living in the age of the chair.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 07:57:49 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/1920xn/p06r2tsx.jpg.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/images/ic/1920xn/p06r2tsx.jpg.webp"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Articles English class]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/europe" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/europe" target="_blank">The Conversation: In-depth analysis, research, news and ideas from leading academics and researchers.</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/a-4-500-year-old-collective-tomb-in-france-reveals-its-secret-the-final-stage-in-the-formation-of-a-european-genome-233382" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/a-4-500-year-old-collective-tomb-in-france-reveals-its-secret-the-final-stage-in-the-formation-of-a-european-genome-233382" target="_blank">A 4,500-year-old collective tomb in France reveals its secret – the final stage in the formation of a ‘European genome’</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/biodiversity-loss-impacts-our-societies-and-economies-how-can-europe-confront-the-spread-of-invasive-species-234598" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/biodiversity-loss-impacts-our-societies-and-economies-how-can-europe-confront-the-spread-of-invasive-species-234598" target="_blank">Biodiversity loss impacts our societies and economies – How can Europe confront the spread of invasive species?</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/is-your-desk-job-killing-your-back-ancient-egyptian-scribes-had-the-same-aches-and-pains-say-researchers-234302" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/is-your-desk-job-killing-your-back-ancient-egyptian-scribes-had-the-same-aches-and-pains-say-researchers-234302" target="_blank">Is your desk job killing your back? Ancient Egyptian scribes had the same aches and pains, say researchers</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/the-chaos-of-choice-how-do-people-pick-their-food-products-230896" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/the-chaos-of-choice-how-do-people-pick-their-food-products-230896" target="_blank">The chaos of choice: how do people pick their food products?</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/the-modern-worlds-relationship-to-time-is-broken-and-its-fuelling-the-rise-of-the-far-right-232630" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/the-modern-worlds-relationship-to-time-is-broken-and-its-fuelling-the-rise-of-the-far-right-232630" target="_blank">The modern world’s relationship to time is broken – and it’s fuelling the rise of the far right</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/teenagers-give-their-tips-to-fight-doomscrolling-236529" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/teenagers-give-their-tips-to-fight-doomscrolling-236529" target="_blank">Teenagers give their tips to fight doomscrolling</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/atlantic-ocean-is-headed-for-a-tipping-point-once-melting-glaciers-shut-down-the-gulf-stream-we-would-see-extreme-climate-change-within-decades-study-shows-222834" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/atlantic-ocean-is-headed-for-a-tipping-point-once-melting-glaciers-shut-down-the-gulf-stream-we-would-see-extreme-climate-change-within-decades-study-shows-222834" target="_blank">Atlantic Ocean is headed for a tipping point − once melting glaciers shut down the Gulf Stream, we would see extreme climate change within decades, study shows</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.wired.com/story/planet-pioneers-nagdaha-small-earth-nepal-soni-pradhanang-ftws-floating-treatment-wetland-systems-water-cleaning-pollution/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.wired.com/story/planet-pioneers-nagdaha-small-earth-nepal-soni-pradhanang-ftws-floating-treatment-wetland-systems-water-cleaning-pollution/" target="_blank">Polluted Lakes Are Being Cleansed Using Floating Wetlands Made of Trash | WIRED</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/how-roads-are-reshaping-and-scarring-our-planet-and-even-changing-animals-dna-231767?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033+CID_190bb945bd07dc4171989d71a0d4939a&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=How%20roads%20are%20reshaping%20and%20scarring%20our%20planet%20and%20even%20changing%20animals%20DNA" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/how-roads-are-reshaping-and-scarring-our-planet-and-even-changing-animals-dna-231767?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033+CID_190bb945bd07dc4171989d71a0d4939a&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=How%20roads%20are%20reshaping%20and%20scarring%20our%20planet%20and%20even%20changing%20animals%20DNA" target="_blank">How roads are reshaping and scarring our planet, and even changing animals’ DNA</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/our-research-reveals-the-scale-of-the-eus-dependency-on-imports-for-critical-minerals-needed-for-the-green-transition-heres-how-that-can-change-230244" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/our-research-reveals-the-scale-of-the-eus-dependency-on-imports-for-critical-minerals-needed-for-the-green-transition-heres-how-that-can-change-230244" target="_blank">Our research reveals the scale of the EU’s dependency on imports for critical minerals needed for the green transition - here’s how that can change</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/why-so-many-people-drown-at-the-waters-edge-231739?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033+CID_190bb945bd07dc4171989d71a0d4939a&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=Why%20so%20many%20people%20drown%20at%20the%20waters%20edge" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/why-so-many-people-drown-at-the-waters-edge-231739?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2025%202024%20-%203044931033+CID_190bb945bd07dc4171989d71a0d4939a&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=Why%20so%20many%20people%20drown%20at%20the%20waters%20edge" target="_blank">Why so many people drown at the water’s edge</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/how-farming-could-change-in-a-post-growth-world-224465" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/how-farming-could-change-in-a-post-growth-world-224465" target="_blank">How farming could change in a post-growth world</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://aeon.co/essays/why-planetary-problems-need-a-new-approach-to-politics?utm_source=Aeon+Newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=d423e76168-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2024_07_16&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_-8e7188468a-%5BLIST_EMAIL_ID%5D" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://aeon.co/essays/why-planetary-problems-need-a-new-approach-to-politics?utm_source=Aeon+Newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=d423e76168-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2024_07_16&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_-8e7188468a-%5BLIST_EMAIL_ID%5D" target="_blank">Why planetary problems need a new approach to politics | Aeon Essays</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.wired.com/story/everything-you-see-is-a-computational-process-if-you-know-how-to-look/?source=Email_0_EDT_WIR_NEWSLETTER_0_DAILY_ZZ&amp;utm_source=nl&amp;utm_brand=wired&amp;utm_mailing=WIR_Daily_071424&amp;utm_campaign=aud-dev&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=WIR_Daily_071424&amp;bxid=5cec24f4fc942d3ada05e83d&amp;cndid=49056848&amp;hasha=063a9be3c3cdcee9024820043b7e10ae&amp;hashb=4fba3b2b5564bfeb1b9676e9d0199688157ceb64&amp;hashc=a6b782719d6d228be03e2408bf7886e3252595b3d240dae270cd2a428e265668&amp;esrc=HeaderAndFooter&amp;utm_term=WIR_Daily_Active" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.wired.com/story/everything-you-see-is-a-computational-process-if-you-know-how-to-look/?source=Email_0_EDT_WIR_NEWSLETTER_0_DAILY_ZZ&amp;utm_source=nl&amp;utm_brand=wired&amp;utm_mailing=WIR_Daily_071424&amp;utm_campaign=aud-dev&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=WIR_Daily_071424&amp;bxid=5cec24f4fc942d3ada05e83d&amp;cndid=49056848&amp;hasha=063a9be3c3cdcee9024820043b7e10ae&amp;hashb=4fba3b2b5564bfeb1b9676e9d0199688157ceb64&amp;hashc=a6b782719d6d228be03e2408bf7886e3252595b3d240dae270cd2a428e265668&amp;esrc=HeaderAndFooter&amp;utm_term=WIR_Daily_Active" target="_blank">Everything You See Is a Computational Process, If You Know How to Look | WIRED</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/new-eu-trade-rules-could-put-poor-countries-in-a-billion-dollar-green-squeeze-228537" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/new-eu-trade-rules-could-put-poor-countries-in-a-billion-dollar-green-squeeze-228537" target="_blank">New EU trade rules could put poor countries in a billion dollar ‘green squeeze’</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/cycling-the-untapped-potential-for-improving-our-health-and-the-climate-228426" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/cycling-the-untapped-potential-for-improving-our-health-and-the-climate-228426" target="_blank">Cycling: The untapped potential for improving our health (and the climate)</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/family-farms-are-fast-disappearing-our-research-shows-how-young-generations-can-take-them-up-successfully-227715" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/family-farms-are-fast-disappearing-our-research-shows-how-young-generations-can-take-them-up-successfully-227715" target="_blank">Family farms are fast disappearing: our research shows how young generations can take them up successfully</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/the-frantic-pace-of-modern-life-is-damaging-our-sense-of-time-but-nature-can-help-us-heal-new-study-223998" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/the-frantic-pace-of-modern-life-is-damaging-our-sense-of-time-but-nature-can-help-us-heal-new-study-223998" target="_blank">The frantic pace of modern life is damaging our sense of time, but nature can help us heal – new study</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/what-did-roman-wine-taste-like-much-better-than-previously-thought-according-to-new-research-223375" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/what-did-roman-wine-taste-like-much-better-than-previously-thought-according-to-new-research-223375" target="_blank">What did Roman wine taste like? Much better than previously thought, according to new research</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/the-first-chemist-in-history-may-have-been-a-female-perfumer-heres-how-the-science-of-scents-has-changed-since-225613?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2023%202024%20-%203009230653&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2023%202024%20-%203009230653+CID_1b9f186096bf76321e24bc7ab3182cb9&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=The%20first%20chemist%20in%20history%20may%20have%20been%20a%20female%20perfumer%20-%20heres%20how%20the%20science%20of%20scents%20has%20changed%20since" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/the-first-chemist-in-history-may-have-been-a-female-perfumer-heres-how-the-science-of-scents-has-changed-since-225613?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2023%202024%20-%203009230653&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2023%202024%20-%203009230653+CID_1b9f186096bf76321e24bc7ab3182cb9&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=The%20first%20chemist%20in%20history%20may%20have%20been%20a%20female%20perfumer%20-%20heres%20how%20the%20science%20of%20scents%20has%20changed%20since" target="_blank">The first chemist in history may have been a female perfumer – here’s how the science of scents has changed since</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/the-science-of-beauty-how-aesthetics-can-boost-your-mood-and-cognition-233023?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2024%202024%20-%203009930659&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2024%202024%20-%203009930659+CID_ae060d298a7b144b55634b4500cc3796&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=The%20science%20of%20beauty%20how%20aesthetics%20can%20boost%20your%20mood%20and%20cognition" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/the-science-of-beauty-how-aesthetics-can-boost-your-mood-and-cognition-233023?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2024%202024%20-%203009930659&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20June%2024%202024%20-%203009930659+CID_ae060d298a7b144b55634b4500cc3796&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=The%20science%20of%20beauty%20how%20aesthetics%20can%20boost%20your%20mood%20and%20cognition" target="_blank">The science of beauty: how aesthetics can boost your mood and cognition</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/two-sleeps-and-devotional-practices-a-look-at-how-people-slept-in-the-17th-century-231890?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%202%202024%20-%203021730751&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%202%202024%20-%203021730751+CID_a65f94eb0522de0aa24af1eceba46e9b&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=Two%20sleeps%20and%20devotional%20practices%20a%20look%20at%20how%20people%20slept%20in%20the%2017th%20century" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/two-sleeps-and-devotional-practices-a-look-at-how-people-slept-in-the-17th-century-231890?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%202%202024%20-%203021730751&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%202%202024%20-%203021730751+CID_a65f94eb0522de0aa24af1eceba46e9b&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=Two%20sleeps%20and%20devotional%20practices%20a%20look%20at%20how%20people%20slept%20in%20the%2017th%20century" target="_blank">‘Two sleeps’ and devotional practices: a look at how people slept in the 17th century</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://aeon.co/essays/we-need-new-metaphors-that-put-life-at-the-centre-of-biology?utm_source=Aeon+Newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=cb6473668b-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2024_07_12&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_-0f6af19dd8-%5BLIST_EMAIL_ID%5D" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://aeon.co/essays/we-need-new-metaphors-that-put-life-at-the-centre-of-biology?utm_source=Aeon+Newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=cb6473668b-EMAIL_CAMPAIGN_2024_07_12&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_term=0_-0f6af19dd8-%5BLIST_EMAIL_ID%5D" target="_blank">We need new metaphors that put life at the centre of biology | Aeon Essays</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/the-first-farmers-often-made-landscapes-more-biodiverse-our-research-could-have-lessons-for-rewilding-today-233272?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2026%202024%20-%203047131055&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2026%202024%20-%203047131055+CID_93a10cb74465469d5bbf8c9319aa3871&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=The%20first%20farmers%20often%20made%20landscapes%20more%20biodiverse%20%20our%20research%20could%20have%20lessons%20for%20rewilding%20today" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/the-first-farmers-often-made-landscapes-more-biodiverse-our-research-could-have-lessons-for-rewilding-today-233272?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2026%202024%20-%203047131055&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%2026%202024%20-%203047131055+CID_93a10cb74465469d5bbf8c9319aa3871&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=The%20first%20farmers%20often%20made%20landscapes%20more%20biodiverse%20%20our%20research%20could%20have%20lessons%20for%20rewilding%20today" target="_blank">The first farmers often made landscapes more biodiverse – our research could have lessons for rewilding today</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/04/opinion/caleb-love-bombing-gaslighting-trauma.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/02/04/opinion/caleb-love-bombing-gaslighting-trauma.html" target="_blank">Opinion | 'Love Bombing,' 'Gaslighting,' and the Rise of 'Trauma-Talk' - The New York Times</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.wired.com/story/dominator-3-tornado-chaser/?source=Email_0_EDT_WIR_NEWSLETTER_0_DAILY_ZZ&amp;utm_source=nl&amp;utm_brand=wired&amp;utm_mailing=WIR_Daily_080424&amp;utm_campaign=aud-dev&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=WIR_Daily_080424&amp;bxid=5cec24f4fc942d3ada05e83d&amp;cndid=49056848&amp;hasha=063a9be3c3cdcee9024820043b7e10ae&amp;hashb=4fba3b2b5564bfeb1b9676e9d0199688157ceb64&amp;hashc=a6b782719d6d228be03e2408bf7886e3252595b3d240dae270cd2a428e265668&amp;esrc=HeaderAndFooter&amp;utm_term=WIR_Daily_Active" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.wired.com/story/dominator-3-tornado-chaser/?source=Email_0_EDT_WIR_NEWSLETTER_0_DAILY_ZZ&amp;utm_source=nl&amp;utm_brand=wired&amp;utm_mailing=WIR_Daily_080424&amp;utm_campaign=aud-dev&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=WIR_Daily_080424&amp;bxid=5cec24f4fc942d3ada05e83d&amp;cndid=49056848&amp;hasha=063a9be3c3cdcee9024820043b7e10ae&amp;hashb=4fba3b2b5564bfeb1b9676e9d0199688157ceb64&amp;hashc=a6b782719d6d228be03e2408bf7886e3252595b3d240dae270cd2a428e265668&amp;esrc=HeaderAndFooter&amp;utm_term=WIR_Daily_Active" target="_blank">To Study Tornados, Bring an Apocalypse-Proof Truck. And Rocket Launchers | WIRED</a>

<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://theconversation.com/whatchamacallit-gizmo-and-thingamajig-what-we-say-when-we-cant-find-the-right-word-and-why-233836?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%208%202024%20-%203026630813&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%208%202024%20-%203026630813+CID_7b88b21feef7bf746b7ad70ffcf18cfd&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=Whatchamacallit%20gizmo%20and%20thingamajig%20what%20we%20say%20when%20we%20cant%20find%20the%20right%20word%20%20and%20why" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/whatchamacallit-gizmo-and-thingamajig-what-we-say-when-we-cant-find-the-right-word-and-why-233836?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%208%202024%20-%203026630813&amp;utm_content=Latest%20from%20The%20Conversation%20for%20July%208%202024%20-%203026630813+CID_7b88b21feef7bf746b7ad70ffcf18cfd&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor_uk&amp;utm_term=Whatchamacallit%20gizmo%20and%20thingamajig%20what%20we%20say%20when%20we%20cant%20find%20the%20right%20word%20%20and%20why" target="_blank">‘Whatchamacallit’, ‘gizmo’ and ‘thingamajig’: what we say when we can’t find the right word – and why</a>

<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.wired.com/story/city-trees-save-lives/" target="_blank">https://www.wired.com/story/city-trees-save-lives/</a><br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://theconversation.com/cramming-for-an-exam-isnt-the-best-way-to-learn-but-if-you-have-to-do-it-heres-how-229761" target="_blank">https://theconversation.com/cramming-for-an-exam-isnt-the-best-way-to-learn-but-if-you-have-to-do-it-heres-how-229761</a>]]></description><link>english/texts/articles-english-class.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/Texts/Articles English class.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 20:26:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[english]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Here we are, materials for English class with Marcel Röthlisberger<br>
navigation on the left, please]]></description><link>english/english.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">english/english.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 08:56:42 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>